<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.5.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-19T11:22:57+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">11 ways weight lifting will save your life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/07/14/11-ways-weight-lifting-will-change-your-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11 ways weight lifting will save your life" /><published>2016-07-14T22:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-07-14T22:54:35+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/07/14/11-ways-weight-lifting-will-change-your-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/07/14/11-ways-weight-lifting-will-change-your-life/">&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting saves my life. It is not merely about what happen in the gym. It is also about the transformation that occurs in my life. Besides looking better, I gain confidence, become more focus and achieve more in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting has that power. Here are &lt;strong&gt;11 ways&lt;/strong&gt; that weight lifting changes your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-youll-look-great&quot;&gt;11. You’ll look great&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lifting weights help you to get lean and toned. You get the healthy shape you are looking for. Cardio might slim you down but you will never achieve that athletic look without implementing resistance training in your life. Ladies, do not worry about getting bulky, it takes a specific hypertrophy program and nutritional plan to gain mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10. Get stronger mentally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you get stronger physically, you will get stronger mentally. Often times, weight lifting requires you to persevere and push yourself to overcome the mental barriers and physical discomfort. It is about moving out of your comfort zone into your uncomfortable zone. If you repeat this simple act for enough time, you will expand your comfort zone. And that is how success happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-prevent-osteoporosis&quot;&gt;9. Prevent osteoporosis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Osteoporosis is a thinning of bone when the formation of new bone is slower than the depletion of bone. Therefore, the bones become brittle and are more prone to fracture. Weight lifting over a period of time can prevent bone loss and even increase bone density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-improve-balance&quot;&gt;8. Improve balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our core is the key to maintaining our balance. You need to activate your core during weight lifting, especially single leg exercises or asymmetrical exercises, to maintain your balance and posture. Through weight lifting, you get stronger in your core muscles and improve your balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-lose-fats&quot;&gt;7. Lose fats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting maintains/builds muscles, increases resting metabolic rate and improves insulin resistance, which are important factors in fat loss. When you only use cardio to manage your weight, you tend to lose fats and muscles, which will decrease your metabolism rate. However, if you add resistance training, and maintain or build muscles, you turn your body to a calories furnace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-better-posture&quot;&gt;6. Better posture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to our sedentary lifestyle, we might be facing muscular imbalances, such as weak back and tight hip flexors. Poor posture could possibly cause negative effects, such as back pain and lower confidence. With weight training, you could strengthen the weaker muscles and improve your posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-boost-self-esteem&quot;&gt;5. Boost self-esteem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you just begin to lift weights, you will notice that you are often setting personal record: lifting heavier weights, improving coordination and lifting more reps. This constant feedback of improvement will make you feel good about yourself and help to improve your self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-increase-focus&quot;&gt;4. Increase focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you lift weights, you will have to focus on your breathing, posture and muscular contraction. Lifting weight with focus on the correct form will translate into increase in concentration on other aspects of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-become-happy&quot;&gt;3. Become happy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a happy pill, exercise is it! Yes, physical exercise lifts your mood and makes you happy. Weight lifting will work wonder for your mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-perform-better-in-other-sports&quot;&gt;2. Perform better in other sports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting improves muscular strength, endurance and coordination. It also helps to prevent sports injuries. If you are already involve in other kind of sports, lifting weights will help you to perform better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-inspire-others&quot;&gt;1. Inspire others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People will notice your changes, be it your body, energy level, productivity or confidence level. They will ask you about your secret. This is your chance to make a difference to others by sharing the benefits of weight lifting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="weight lifting" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">Weight lifting saves my life. It is not merely about what happen in the gym. It is also about the transformation that occurs in my life. Besides looking better, I gain confidence, become more focus and achieve more in my life. Weight lifting has that power. Here are 11 ways that weight lifting changes your life. 11. You’ll look great Lifting weights help you to get lean and toned. You get the healthy shape you are looking for. Cardio might slim you down but you will never achieve that athletic look without implementing resistance training in your life. Ladies, do not worry about getting bulky, it takes a specific hypertrophy program and nutritional plan to gain mass. 10. Get stronger mentally As you get stronger physically, you will get stronger mentally. Often times, weight lifting requires you to persevere and push yourself to overcome the mental barriers and physical discomfort. It is about moving out of your comfort zone into your uncomfortable zone. If you repeat this simple act for enough time, you will expand your comfort zone. And that is how success happens. 9. Prevent osteoporosis Osteoporosis is a thinning of bone when the formation of new bone is slower than the depletion of bone. Therefore, the bones become brittle and are more prone to fracture. Weight lifting over a period of time can prevent bone loss and even increase bone density. 8. Improve balance Our core is the key to maintaining our balance. You need to activate your core during weight lifting, especially single leg exercises or asymmetrical exercises, to maintain your balance and posture. Through weight lifting, you get stronger in your core muscles and improve your balance. 7. Lose fats Weight lifting maintains/builds muscles, increases resting metabolic rate and improves insulin resistance, which are important factors in fat loss. When you only use cardio to manage your weight, you tend to lose fats and muscles, which will decrease your metabolism rate. However, if you add resistance training, and maintain or build muscles, you turn your body to a calories furnace. 6. Better posture Due to our sedentary lifestyle, we might be facing muscular imbalances, such as weak back and tight hip flexors. Poor posture could possibly cause negative effects, such as back pain and lower confidence. With weight training, you could strengthen the weaker muscles and improve your posture. 5. Boost self-esteem If you just begin to lift weights, you will notice that you are often setting personal record: lifting heavier weights, improving coordination and lifting more reps. This constant feedback of improvement will make you feel good about yourself and help to improve your self-esteem. 4. Increase focus When you lift weights, you will have to focus on your breathing, posture and muscular contraction. Lifting weight with focus on the correct form will translate into increase in concentration on other aspects of your life. 3. Become happy If there is a happy pill, exercise is it! Yes, physical exercise lifts your mood and makes you happy. Weight lifting will work wonder for your mental health. 2. Perform better in other sports Weight lifting improves muscular strength, endurance and coordination. It also helps to prevent sports injuries. If you are already involve in other kind of sports, lifting weights will help you to perform better. 1. Inspire others People will notice your changes, be it your body, energy level, productivity or confidence level. They will ask you about your secret. This is your chance to make a difference to others by sharing the benefits of weight lifting.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combat your excuses: Try this 10 minutes body weight workout!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/04/18/try-this-10-mins-workout/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combat your excuses: Try this 10 minutes body weight workout!" /><published>2016-04-18T13:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-04-18T13:54:35+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/04/18/try-this-10-mins-workout</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/04/18/try-this-10-mins-workout/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;which-is-more-precious-time-or-health&quot;&gt;Which is more precious? Time or health?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, I hear people they do not have time to manage their health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is, in the long run, the lack of health maintenance will cost them more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do we have to choose between the two? Why do the both of them have to be mutually exclusive?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use to believe that if I miss one day of training, I will deteriorate. I use to practice yoga for 1 hour and dance for 1 hour. That’s not counting the time I have to travel to dance classes and watch dance videos. On top of that, I have to prepare my breakfast and lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If chronic obsession with dance is a thing, I have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder other aspects of my life are not going anywhere for me. Now, I exercise an hour a day, 3-5 days a week, and I feel much fitter, stronger and healthier. Some days, when things get hectic, I do 10 minutes body weight workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-am-in-better-balance&quot;&gt;I am in better balance.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am managing my time optimally. I know how to train smarter. I understand my priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I realize exercise comes after &lt;em&gt;non-exercise activity thermogenesis&lt;/em&gt; (NEAT) in the aspects of health.  NEAT is the calories expended outside of eating, exercising and sleeping. Basically becoming less sedentary, i.e. sitting less, should be looked into before contemplating about hitting the gym for an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be another me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t fall into the trap of thinking that more always equals to better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steady state cardio workouts that last for more than 45 minutes have their own unique benefits. You can continue this form of exercise if you enjoy it. However, if you are someone like me, looking to slot in short bursts of workout in a time crammed lifestyle, here is a &lt;strong&gt;workout program that is just going to take you 10 minutes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-minutesbody-weight-workout&quot;&gt;10 minutes body weight workout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get your interval timer ready. The magic of short workout is in the burst of energy. It will only work if you push yourself to more than 70% of your effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–If you are new to circuit training, you want to work in 30s and rest for 30s. (Or feel free to go into any intervals that are more suitable for you.)
If you are familiar with circuit training, we are not going to take any rest. You are going to run through these 10 exercises in 1 minute interval each.–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;burpees&quot;&gt;Burpees&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From standing position, squat down and place both of your palms firmly on the floor. From this position either hop or walk back into a plank position. From the plank position, again, either hop or walk back into a squatting position. Explode into a jump or just stand and rise onto the balls of your feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;squats&quot;&gt;Squats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your feet are firmly grounded and aligned with your knee. Tighten your glutes muscles (butt). Hinge from your hips. Lead your squat with your glutes. Imagine that you are sitting down on a chair behind you. If you are fit, add an explosive hop when coming out from your squat position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-knees&quot;&gt;High knees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have your hands in front of you at hips level. Lift your knees such that your knees touch your palms. Make sure you are not rounding your back in this exercise. Go as fast as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rear-lunges&quot;&gt;Rear lunges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take your right foot back and go into a lunge position. Step back into lunge position. Alternate the feet that step back each time. If you feel that you could do more, switch legs with a hop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-plank-with-left-arm-on-floor&quot;&gt;Side plank with left arm on floor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engage your core and hold yourself up in a side plank position. If you feel strong, straighten your right arm, such that your arms and body form a t shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inchworm&quot;&gt;Inchworm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a standing position, bend forward such that your palms are down on the floor. Walk your hands out to a pushup position while keeping your legs straight. Walk your hands back towards your legs and straighten your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-plank-with-right-arm-on-floor&quot;&gt;Side plank with right arm on floor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is to balance out the previous side plank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;glute-bridge&quot;&gt;Glute bridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lie supine with knees bend. Contract your glutes and lift into a bridge position, making sure not to compress your lower back. Lower yourself down without allowing your glutes to touch the floor. And lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lateral-crawl&quot;&gt;Lateral crawl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start in a pushup position with your core tight. Cross your right arm over your left arm and move towards the left, coordinating the leg movements with the hands movement. Move 5 times to the left. And repeat on the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elbow-plank&quot;&gt;Elbow plank&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have your elbows on the floor. Tighten all your muscles and go into a plank pose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you just finish a 10 minutes workout. If you still feel like going, repeat this round.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="body weight workout" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">Which is more precious? Time or health? Often, I hear people they do not have time to manage their health. The irony is, in the long run, the lack of health maintenance will cost them more time. Why do we have to choose between the two? Why do the both of them have to be mutually exclusive? I use to believe that if I miss one day of training, I will deteriorate. I use to practice yoga for 1 hour and dance for 1 hour. That’s not counting the time I have to travel to dance classes and watch dance videos. On top of that, I have to prepare my breakfast and lunch. If chronic obsession with dance is a thing, I have it. No wonder other aspects of my life are not going anywhere for me. Now, I exercise an hour a day, 3-5 days a week, and I feel much fitter, stronger and healthier. Some days, when things get hectic, I do 10 minutes body weight workout. I am in better balance. I am managing my time optimally. I know how to train smarter. I understand my priorities. In fact, I realize exercise comes after non-exercise activity thermogenesis (NEAT) in the aspects of health.  NEAT is the calories expended outside of eating, exercising and sleeping. Basically becoming less sedentary, i.e. sitting less, should be looked into before contemplating about hitting the gym for an hour. Don’t be another me. Don’t fall into the trap of thinking that more always equals to better. Steady state cardio workouts that last for more than 45 minutes have their own unique benefits. You can continue this form of exercise if you enjoy it. However, if you are someone like me, looking to slot in short bursts of workout in a time crammed lifestyle, here is a workout program that is just going to take you 10 minutes. 10 minutes body weight workout Get your interval timer ready. The magic of short workout is in the burst of energy. It will only work if you push yourself to more than 70% of your effort. –If you are new to circuit training, you want to work in 30s and rest for 30s. (Or feel free to go into any intervals that are more suitable for you.) If you are familiar with circuit training, we are not going to take any rest. You are going to run through these 10 exercises in 1 minute interval each.– Burpees From standing position, squat down and place both of your palms firmly on the floor. From this position either hop or walk back into a plank position. From the plank position, again, either hop or walk back into a squatting position. Explode into a jump or just stand and rise onto the balls of your feet. Squats Make sure your feet are firmly grounded and aligned with your knee. Tighten your glutes muscles (butt). Hinge from your hips. Lead your squat with your glutes. Imagine that you are sitting down on a chair behind you. If you are fit, add an explosive hop when coming out from your squat position. High knees Have your hands in front of you at hips level. Lift your knees such that your knees touch your palms. Make sure you are not rounding your back in this exercise. Go as fast as you can. Rear lunges Take your right foot back and go into a lunge position. Step back into lunge position. Alternate the feet that step back each time. If you feel that you could do more, switch legs with a hop. Side plank with left arm on floor Engage your core and hold yourself up in a side plank position. If you feel strong, straighten your right arm, such that your arms and body form a t shape. Inchworm From a standing position, bend forward such that your palms are down on the floor. Walk your hands out to a pushup position while keeping your legs straight. Walk your hands back towards your legs and straighten your body. Side plank with right arm on floor This is to balance out the previous side plank. Glute bridge Lie supine with knees bend. Contract your glutes and lift into a bridge position, making sure not to compress your lower back. Lower yourself down without allowing your glutes to touch the floor. And lift. Lateral crawl Start in a pushup position with your core tight. Cross your right arm over your left arm and move towards the left, coordinating the leg movements with the hands movement. Move 5 times to the left. And repeat on the right side. Elbow plank Have your elbows on the floor. Tighten all your muscles and go into a plank pose. And you just finish a 10 minutes workout. If you still feel like going, repeat this round.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How weight lifting saves my life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/03/26/how-weight-lifting-saves-my-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How weight lifting saves my life" /><published>2016-03-26T13:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-03-26T13:54:35+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/03/26/how-weight-lifting-saves-my-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/03/26/how-weight-lifting-saves-my-life/">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt that you are not good enough for your role? I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a fitness instructor and I used to feel like I am a fraud. I am 1.63m with a weight of 54kg. I have a BMI of around 20 and that should be considered healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-the-truth-is-im-skinny-fat&quot;&gt;But the truth is I’m skinny fat.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am slim but I have muffin tops. Basically, I am flabby. And truth be told, when it comes to skinny for Asian, I am no where near that. I look into the mirror and I feel unconvincing. I did not suffer from body image issues but I believe I could be better. At the same time, my fitness career is going nowhere. Classes come and go. My financial and work life is a wreck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the practice of yoga teaches me how to love and appreciate myself for who I am and for where I am at. I know I have to look forward and ignite the change necessary for me to become who I want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-weight-lifting-comes-into-my-life&quot;&gt;And weight lifting comes into my life.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting knocks on my heart almost like how yoga comes into my life as an epiphany. I have faith in the calling of my heart. So far, it hasn’t failed me. It has always shown me the direction that I need to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I got my friend to show me the ropes. Soon after, I find myself reading articles and books on weightlifting until I am confident enough to step into the gym alone. Today, I step in the gym with my own exercise plan. I lift the weights with a vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout my journey, I build up muscles and tone my body. And most importantly, I see the way I handle my business transform as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use to be passive, waiting for people to contact me for business. I used to share my services like I am not fully confident of it. Now, I’m actively networking and creating meaningful relationship. I am seeking out mentorship and surrounding myself with successful and wise people. I speak of my business with faith and conviction. Most importantly, I know my services are of high value and it could transform people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;because-i-have-been-through-the-transformation-myself&quot;&gt;Because I have been through the transformation myself.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the exhilaration that I feel when I lift 40kg off the floor. It’s the feeling that I got when I lift more than I did previously. It’s the focus that I need to lift in proper form. It’s the correction of my posture that gives me confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I stand in front of students, friends and strangers, knowing fully that I am good enough. Knowing that I understand different muscles groups and how they function. Knowing that I could guide a class safely and effectively. Knowing that my services work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weight-lifting-saves-my-life&quot;&gt;Weight lifting saves my life.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting also reminds me that I could push pass my own mental limits and create records for myself. It shows me that progress comes with careful planning. At the same time, it shows me that I have to drop my ego in front of the weights, if not I will risk injuring myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In yoga, I am taught that our physical world is intricately linked to our internal world. How we do one thing is how we do everything. Through the internal workings, weight lifting brings upon to me a new world and possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-breaks-the-old-me-down&quot;&gt;It breaks the old me down.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new me is created and strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my life, I appreciate coming into contact with yoga and weightlifting. It challenges my perspective and allows me to learn more about life and myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today, I am at peace. Today, I am who I need to be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="weight lifting" /><category term="self-esteem" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">Have you ever felt that you are not good enough for your role? I have. I am a fitness instructor and I used to feel like I am a fraud. I am 1.63m with a weight of 54kg. I have a BMI of around 20 and that should be considered healthy. But the truth is I’m skinny fat. I am slim but I have muffin tops. Basically, I am flabby. And truth be told, when it comes to skinny for Asian, I am no where near that. I look into the mirror and I feel unconvincing. I did not suffer from body image issues but I believe I could be better. At the same time, my fitness career is going nowhere. Classes come and go. My financial and work life is a wreck. Luckily, the practice of yoga teaches me how to love and appreciate myself for who I am and for where I am at. I know I have to look forward and ignite the change necessary for me to become who I want to be. And weight lifting comes into my life. Weight lifting knocks on my heart almost like how yoga comes into my life as an epiphany. I have faith in the calling of my heart. So far, it hasn’t failed me. It has always shown me the direction that I need to be. Initially, I got my friend to show me the ropes. Soon after, I find myself reading articles and books on weightlifting until I am confident enough to step into the gym alone. Today, I step in the gym with my own exercise plan. I lift the weights with a vision. Throughout my journey, I build up muscles and tone my body. And most importantly, I see the way I handle my business transform as well. I use to be passive, waiting for people to contact me for business. I used to share my services like I am not fully confident of it. Now, I’m actively networking and creating meaningful relationship. I am seeking out mentorship and surrounding myself with successful and wise people. I speak of my business with faith and conviction. Most importantly, I know my services are of high value and it could transform people. Because I have been through the transformation myself. It is the exhilaration that I feel when I lift 40kg off the floor. It’s the feeling that I got when I lift more than I did previously. It’s the focus that I need to lift in proper form. It’s the correction of my posture that gives me confidence. Today, I stand in front of students, friends and strangers, knowing fully that I am good enough. Knowing that I understand different muscles groups and how they function. Knowing that I could guide a class safely and effectively. Knowing that my services work. Weight lifting saves my life. Weight lifting also reminds me that I could push pass my own mental limits and create records for myself. It shows me that progress comes with careful planning. At the same time, it shows me that I have to drop my ego in front of the weights, if not I will risk injuring myself. In yoga, I am taught that our physical world is intricately linked to our internal world. How we do one thing is how we do everything. Through the internal workings, weight lifting brings upon to me a new world and possibilities. It breaks the old me down. A new me is created and strengthened. In my life, I appreciate coming into contact with yoga and weightlifting. It challenges my perspective and allows me to learn more about life and myself. Today, I am at peace. Today, I am who I need to be.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I’m a broke, ohm-chanting and time-altering dragon</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/musings/2016/02/21/im-a-broke-ohm-chanting-and-time-altering-dragon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I'm a broke, ohm-chanting and time-altering dragon" /><published>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/musings/2016/02/21/im-a-broke-ohm-chanting-and-time-altering-dragon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/musings/2016/02/21/im-a-broke-ohm-chanting-and-time-altering-dragon/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;monday-tuesday-wednesday-to-saturday&quot;&gt;Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday to Saturday.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days repeat themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day, or maybe the same old yet different day. The escalator transports me upwards to the exit of the MRT station. It’s 3.25pm, work will start at 3.30pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am wearing a blue T-shirt that shouts volunteer at the back, and a knee-length navy blue yoga pants. I think I have worn them together last week and perhaps on a Tuesday too. Upon exiting the MRT station, a huge display screen of the shopping mall plays the same advertisement, which I can’t help but notice despite the fact that I never give much attention to this buzz. Most of the advertisements bully you to the way they think it is best for you to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-go-back-to-the-morning&quot;&gt;Let’s go back to the morning.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a yoga class, the weekly practice session that will prepare me to be a teacher. That is why I’m carrying my yoga mat to work. It starts at 10.30am, I must have reached around 10.35am. Everyone in class is sitting cross-legged with their eyes close, with the voice of my yoga teacher sailing through the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If there are divine beings, this is the place they will choose to reside.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to walk silently, not wanting my intrusion to break their focus. But the nature of the dance floor makes it impossible to take a step without announcing my arrival. It screeches away defiantly no matter how light I tread. Once, I remember I was lying down and somebody walked around my head and I thought I am going to be trample by an elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, with an outward look of poise, nobody so much as move even their eyes. If this is in a forest, a squirrel might just land on one of their laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not like them, I would be fidgeting and guessing who it is each time someone walks across the room. But luckily, they are not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I flow into the practice, feeling at ease and abandoning any thoughts that I have intruded the practice. Practice, in all solemnness should be practical and present. One should try to clear the disturbances of one’s mind during practice. It is to observe and let go whatever surfaces and bring our focus back to the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indeed, it is not going to be fairies prancing around magical toadstool or even prayer circles to wish for the ever elusive world peace, a slogan of the flower children in the hippie years, accompanied with long beards, filth-accumulating naked bodies and bare foot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;at-12pm&quot;&gt;At 12pm.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We give our thanks and ready ourselves for the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of yoga is flow and the composure to face changes. The yoga class has ended and is ended. Today is the last day of our weekly session. It has been eight months since it all begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it feels that there is a deep transformational power within me, like a dragon arising from her century-long slumber, ready to soar. I’m ready for whatever the world is going to throw at me and I will face it with zen and peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are days which I thought I know what Buddha must have been through, living off nothing but feeling contentment and being dedicated to the arduous task of spreading his teachings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I live with nothing, relatively. I proclaim myself the great spiritual seeker who can subsist on the minimal. Of course, I can live with all this illusion until it is time to pay for my bills and I need to seek help from my parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-felt-like-a-hypocrite&quot;&gt;I felt like a hypocrite.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balloon for chest puncture at this very moment. I cannot live next to nothing. For that, I’m sure Buddha doesn’t have to pay bills. Definitely the electricity, water and food did not come about because I sow seeds of love through the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything, of course is being well taken care of by my parents.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;18-march-2014&quot;&gt;18 March 2014.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might not be so different from 18 March 2010 after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I transform yet I am also back to where I begin, the lost and broke-ass kid of lofty dreams, living an idealistic life, traversing upon leaps and mountains of disapproval of others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, at twenty four, five years of searching, having been through what should be an incredible journey towards light and enlightenment, I am still in debts. The love did not manage to convince my local government to dissolve my debts. They would probably tell me to be grateful that they did not increase the interest rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-them-im-just-a-hobo&quot;&gt;To them, I’m just a hobo.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so be it. God, Buddha, or whoever up there did not patronize my efforts of tender love towards their creations or universal consciousness or oneness or divinity or nothingness. I am not even close, maybe I’m the wolf in sheep clothing in the spiritual world, in which I believe that I’m a sheep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;year-2014&quot;&gt;Year 2014.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still greedy and with many desires in my life that it is in complete opposition in the practice of contentment. Even when it is nearing the end of my yoga teacher training, I am still sitting on the fence of six thousand dollars of debt (my polytechnic school fees and part of my yoga teacher training fees) and of living off my parents shamelessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I’m positioned precariously, with the danger of falling to the abyss of immobility, I am planning for my next dive trip, hankering for Bali to learn tribal fusion belly dance and even dreaming of scoring a permaculture certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still after eight months of yoga pursuit, in which I learn that yoga essentially means a state of clarity, I am an unstable and highly unreliable human being.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of becoming more clear-eyed about the one thing that I should devote myself to, I morph into a multi-headed, ohm-chanting, serene looking, juice-sipping dragon or if you prefer wolf in sheep’s skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I discredit myself any further, there is at least one thing that I am living in accordance to the philosophy of yoga. It is that I should do my best without attaching myself to the results. I’m taking this path seriously and flowing with the wind throughout my efforts to soar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am biologically twenty four, spiritually nutcase, monetary broke, but at least physically and mentally, I feel at my best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if my erected spine has free itself from the messy affair with gravity. The lower half of my body is grounded like it should be, but I could stand as if heaven has attached a string to my upper half of my body. Maybe there is a help line send from up above after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am without traces of age lines on my face, without the impairment of the spine through constant slouching in modern day living. With my suppleness, I am going through the best ride of my life, at this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe, I turn back time or maybe the way I’m living is simply topsy-turvy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems yesterday is a far shot but eight months ago is just within stretch and tomorrow, who knows. Time is a funny thing and the only logical thing one could do is to be present. And maybe, if I hang on a little more, I would have wings strong enough to soar with the multi heads of my greedy dragon. I would be able to piece it all together and live through it as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But now is not the time to worry because I am truly at the best moment of my life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><category term="live your dream" /><category term="passion" /><summary type="html">Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday to Saturday. These days repeat themselves. Another day, or maybe the same old yet different day. The escalator transports me upwards to the exit of the MRT station. It’s 3.25pm, work will start at 3.30pm. I am wearing a blue T-shirt that shouts volunteer at the back, and a knee-length navy blue yoga pants. I think I have worn them together last week and perhaps on a Tuesday too. Upon exiting the MRT station, a huge display screen of the shopping mall plays the same advertisement, which I can’t help but notice despite the fact that I never give much attention to this buzz. Most of the advertisements bully you to the way they think it is best for you to live. Let’s go back to the morning. I have a yoga class, the weekly practice session that will prepare me to be a teacher. That is why I’m carrying my yoga mat to work. It starts at 10.30am, I must have reached around 10.35am. Everyone in class is sitting cross-legged with their eyes close, with the voice of my yoga teacher sailing through the air. If there are divine beings, this is the place they will choose to reside. I try to walk silently, not wanting my intrusion to break their focus. But the nature of the dance floor makes it impossible to take a step without announcing my arrival. It screeches away defiantly no matter how light I tread. Once, I remember I was lying down and somebody walked around my head and I thought I am going to be trample by an elephant. Still, with an outward look of poise, nobody so much as move even their eyes. If this is in a forest, a squirrel might just land on one of their laps. I am not like them, I would be fidgeting and guessing who it is each time someone walks across the room. But luckily, they are not me. I flow into the practice, feeling at ease and abandoning any thoughts that I have intruded the practice. Practice, in all solemnness should be practical and present. One should try to clear the disturbances of one’s mind during practice. It is to observe and let go whatever surfaces and bring our focus back to the practice. Indeed, it is not going to be fairies prancing around magical toadstool or even prayer circles to wish for the ever elusive world peace, a slogan of the flower children in the hippie years, accompanied with long beards, filth-accumulating naked bodies and bare foot. At 12pm. We give our thanks and ready ourselves for the world. The beauty of yoga is flow and the composure to face changes. The yoga class has ended and is ended. Today is the last day of our weekly session. It has been eight months since it all begins. Sometimes it feels that there is a deep transformational power within me, like a dragon arising from her century-long slumber, ready to soar. I’m ready for whatever the world is going to throw at me and I will face it with zen and peace. Yes, there are days which I thought I know what Buddha must have been through, living off nothing but feeling contentment and being dedicated to the arduous task of spreading his teachings. Because I live with nothing, relatively. I proclaim myself the great spiritual seeker who can subsist on the minimal. Of course, I can live with all this illusion until it is time to pay for my bills and I need to seek help from my parents. I felt like a hypocrite. A balloon for chest puncture at this very moment. I cannot live next to nothing. For that, I’m sure Buddha doesn’t have to pay bills. Definitely the electricity, water and food did not come about because I sow seeds of love through the universe. Everything, of course is being well taken care of by my parents. 18 March 2014. It might not be so different from 18 March 2010 after all. I transform yet I am also back to where I begin, the lost and broke-ass kid of lofty dreams, living an idealistic life, traversing upon leaps and mountains of disapproval of others. Today, at twenty four, five years of searching, having been through what should be an incredible journey towards light and enlightenment, I am still in debts. The love did not manage to convince my local government to dissolve my debts. They would probably tell me to be grateful that they did not increase the interest rate. To them, I’m just a hobo. And so be it. God, Buddha, or whoever up there did not patronize my efforts of tender love towards their creations or universal consciousness or oneness or divinity or nothingness. I am not even close, maybe I’m the wolf in sheep clothing in the spiritual world, in which I believe that I’m a sheep. Year 2014. I am still greedy and with many desires in my life that it is in complete opposition in the practice of contentment. Even when it is nearing the end of my yoga teacher training, I am still sitting on the fence of six thousand dollars of debt (my polytechnic school fees and part of my yoga teacher training fees) and of living off my parents shamelessly. Even when I’m positioned precariously, with the danger of falling to the abyss of immobility, I am planning for my next dive trip, hankering for Bali to learn tribal fusion belly dance and even dreaming of scoring a permaculture certification. Still after eight months of yoga pursuit, in which I learn that yoga essentially means a state of clarity, I am an unstable and highly unreliable human being. Instead of becoming more clear-eyed about the one thing that I should devote myself to, I morph into a multi-headed, ohm-chanting, serene looking, juice-sipping dragon or if you prefer wolf in sheep’s skin. Before I discredit myself any further, there is at least one thing that I am living in accordance to the philosophy of yoga. It is that I should do my best without attaching myself to the results. I’m taking this path seriously and flowing with the wind throughout my efforts to soar. Today. I am biologically twenty four, spiritually nutcase, monetary broke, but at least physically and mentally, I feel at my best. As if my erected spine has free itself from the messy affair with gravity. The lower half of my body is grounded like it should be, but I could stand as if heaven has attached a string to my upper half of my body. Maybe there is a help line send from up above after all. I am without traces of age lines on my face, without the impairment of the spine through constant slouching in modern day living. With my suppleness, I am going through the best ride of my life, at this moment. Maybe, I turn back time or maybe the way I’m living is simply topsy-turvy. It seems yesterday is a far shot but eight months ago is just within stretch and tomorrow, who knows. Time is a funny thing and the only logical thing one could do is to be present. And maybe, if I hang on a little more, I would have wings strong enough to soar with the multi heads of my greedy dragon. I would be able to piece it all together and live through it as a whole. But now is not the time to worry because I am truly at the best moment of my life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lets be an artist now</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/musings/2016/02/21/lets-be-an-artist-now/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lets be an artist now" /><published>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/musings/2016/02/21/lets-be-an-artist-now</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/musings/2016/02/21/lets-be-an-artist-now/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-this-moment-sit-alone&quot;&gt;For this moment, sit alone.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow the buzz of the world to pass and listen closely to your heart’s desire. Perhaps, you would hear this voice inside of you. This voice is urging you shyly, slowly but surely, like a tortoise emerging from its’ shell. It could be so soft that it is almost inaudible to you, because you have never given it too much attention. But give it a little more time, you would hear that this voice in you is crying out for you to play, to play boundlessly and freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It wishes for you to celebrate the moment and simply live in the now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are patient to realize, you hear that this voice is nurturing an artist. Not the hot shot mega million rock star kind of artist, but the artist who is approachable, the artist, who is someone real, someone like you. There is an artist in you waiting to emerge if only you believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-are-all-born-to-create&quot;&gt;We are all born to create.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spend much of our childhood imagining that we are captains sailing the ferocious sea, the jungle explorers stumbling on the next miracle herb for mankind, or even the sages working to solve the puzzle of the grand web of life. Of course, we might have one or two teddy bears which we would do voice over for. And we host our own kids’ entertainment channel, on par with Teletubbies and Blue Clues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The world is full of possibilities and magic.&lt;/strong&gt;
Then, we go to school where creating become mandatory, more than that, creativity becomes a chore and is stuffed into a box of grades and criticism. At the same time, we have to manage living in the cauldron of grades, expectations, mini-skirts, and the funny feeling towards the opposite sex. Bit by bit, we lose that little connection with simply making things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, I say it, creating art isn’t anything noble, it isn’t all about creating The Last Supper, Mona Lisa or David. Yes, it could become something recognized, but art, strips to its’ base, is just making things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;art-is-play&quot;&gt;Art is play.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The word play is defiant, it rejects fitting into a singular form.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Play could involve legos, words, bodily movements, colors, flowers, cars, papers, photos, aubergines, chickpeas, knives, seedlings and so much more. Play would involve destruction and creation, no matter which form it takes. Even writers have to continuously depart with words they love. Art is a micro version of nature, the constant cycle of destruction and creation. Perhaps it is this reason why one could feel so much alive and at one with the universe when creating art. Some would call this experience being in the flow. Whatever you call it, it is real and so real that sometimes everything else becomes an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you create art, you chuck the ominous question of the purpose of one’s existence to one side.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could leave that to the philosophers to figure and argue among them for now. At this moment, when you are at one with your art, your soul resonates with the rhythm of the universe. And it is particularly in this state that you understand that this is all that you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;all-the-layers-of-crises-fall-apart-and&quot;&gt;All the layers of crises fall apart. and&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others might ask if this is your form of escapade from the reality. And perhaps, this is the time to retrieve the question on the purpose of one existence and to question reality. What is reality exactly? Is it this environment of sterility and control whereby your every action could be spied by a particular person? Is it reality where you have to be living under surveillance and thronging among the crowd anonymously? Is this what is to be perceived as reality? The subject of reality is as broad as play could be, so why would one shackle another on the threat of reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##So please don’t let the voices of others drown the timid voice in you.##&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could be a dancer feeling the vibrations of music in our limbs, or a poet riding the tempo of words, or a photographer capturing the light of fleeting nature into eternity. This you could all be and even more in your life. You could be a low-wage worker, a farmer, a white collar, a top-level executive or a medical doctor. Whatever it is, you need not be in constant conflict with the voice crying out to create art. Because art transcends the boundaries of identities and labels. And through art, you would discover that you have lost yourself only to ultimately reconnect with the universe once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Only if you listen to that timid voice inside you.
Only if you take the courage to step in faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, through many cycles of construction, destruction, agony, happiness, emptiness, contentment, separation, unity and transcending, your world could never be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="finding motivation" /><category term="passion" /><category term="live your dream" /><summary type="html">For this moment, sit alone. Allow the buzz of the world to pass and listen closely to your heart’s desire. Perhaps, you would hear this voice inside of you. This voice is urging you shyly, slowly but surely, like a tortoise emerging from its’ shell. It could be so soft that it is almost inaudible to you, because you have never given it too much attention. But give it a little more time, you would hear that this voice in you is crying out for you to play, to play boundlessly and freely. It wishes for you to celebrate the moment and simply live in the now. If you are patient to realize, you hear that this voice is nurturing an artist. Not the hot shot mega million rock star kind of artist, but the artist who is approachable, the artist, who is someone real, someone like you. There is an artist in you waiting to emerge if only you believe. We are all born to create. We spend much of our childhood imagining that we are captains sailing the ferocious sea, the jungle explorers stumbling on the next miracle herb for mankind, or even the sages working to solve the puzzle of the grand web of life. Of course, we might have one or two teddy bears which we would do voice over for. And we host our own kids’ entertainment channel, on par with Teletubbies and Blue Clues. The world is full of possibilities and magic. Then, we go to school where creating become mandatory, more than that, creativity becomes a chore and is stuffed into a box of grades and criticism. At the same time, we have to manage living in the cauldron of grades, expectations, mini-skirts, and the funny feeling towards the opposite sex. Bit by bit, we lose that little connection with simply making things up. There, I say it, creating art isn’t anything noble, it isn’t all about creating The Last Supper, Mona Lisa or David. Yes, it could become something recognized, but art, strips to its’ base, is just making things up. Art is play. The word play is defiant, it rejects fitting into a singular form. Play could involve legos, words, bodily movements, colors, flowers, cars, papers, photos, aubergines, chickpeas, knives, seedlings and so much more. Play would involve destruction and creation, no matter which form it takes. Even writers have to continuously depart with words they love. Art is a micro version of nature, the constant cycle of destruction and creation. Perhaps it is this reason why one could feel so much alive and at one with the universe when creating art. Some would call this experience being in the flow. Whatever you call it, it is real and so real that sometimes everything else becomes an illusion. When you create art, you chuck the ominous question of the purpose of one’s existence to one side. You could leave that to the philosophers to figure and argue among them for now. At this moment, when you are at one with your art, your soul resonates with the rhythm of the universe. And it is particularly in this state that you understand that this is all that you need. All the layers of crises fall apart. and They cease to exist. Others might ask if this is your form of escapade from the reality. And perhaps, this is the time to retrieve the question on the purpose of one existence and to question reality. What is reality exactly? Is it this environment of sterility and control whereby your every action could be spied by a particular person? Is it reality where you have to be living under surveillance and thronging among the crowd anonymously? Is this what is to be perceived as reality? The subject of reality is as broad as play could be, so why would one shackle another on the threat of reality? ##So please don’t let the voices of others drown the timid voice in you.## You could be a dancer feeling the vibrations of music in our limbs, or a poet riding the tempo of words, or a photographer capturing the light of fleeting nature into eternity. This you could all be and even more in your life. You could be a low-wage worker, a farmer, a white collar, a top-level executive or a medical doctor. Whatever it is, you need not be in constant conflict with the voice crying out to create art. Because art transcends the boundaries of identities and labels. And through art, you would discover that you have lost yourself only to ultimately reconnect with the universe once more. ##Only if you listen to that timid voice inside you. Only if you take the courage to step in faith. Then, through many cycles of construction, destruction, agony, happiness, emptiness, contentment, separation, unity and transcending, your world could never be the same again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 ways to increase your commitment to weight management program</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/02/21/4-ways-to-increase-commitment-to-weight-loss/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 ways to increase your commitment to weight management program" /><published>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/02/21/4-ways-to-increase-commitment-to-weight-loss</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2016/02/21/4-ways-to-increase-commitment-to-weight-loss/">&lt;p&gt;What is the first thing that you think about when people mention weight loss?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people will conjure up images of deprivation. Not being able to eat the food they like. Endless exercises. Running like a gazelle. Giving up the comfort of their cosy chair. Moving around a place full of self-obsessed people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is precisely this line of thought that prevents people from starting a weight management program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I did not start out loving the gym.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to tell me 5 years ago that I will love hanging out in the gym, I will think that you are crazy. I’m not selling you a castle in the cloud, I’m talking about sustainable changes that will stage you up for success in your weight management program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I’m going to tell you how you could increase your commitment to weight management plan and avoid the pitfall of self-sabotaging behaviors like “I’m not good enough”, “It’s too scary” or “I’m never getting there”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-start-easy&quot;&gt;4. Start easy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you apply for CEO when you just graduate from school? Changes are you start as an executive on the lower management level. So why is it that when people approach weight loss, they change their diet and exercise from one extreme to the other extreme? After a few days, they start to have cravings and they have to struggle with their willpower. Yes, some people have super willpower to succeed this way. But for one person that succeed, there are many more who will scrap their diet change as a failure and think that there is no point in doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s much easier to start with small changes and work towards your ultimate goal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are just starting out, even eating one healthy meal or exercising once a week is a great start. Once it becomes habitual, you can start increasing the amount of healthy food, cutting the calories and exercising more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-have-a-structured-plan&quot;&gt;3. Have a structured plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not always a fan of having a structured plan. But over the years, I feel that having a structured plan will reduce my needs to rely on my emotions to make decision. Of course, it is great that if you are feeling motivated and are hitting the gym, exercising regularly and eating clean. But what happen if you are not feeling your very best and decide to skip the gym for one day, and then the next, and then the next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Having a structured plan reduces the guesswork and need to rely on willpower.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it as specify as possible. If Thursday is your legs day, on Wednesday night, plan out the time you are going to the gym, exact exercises, reps, sets. I will go so far as to even plan the rest time in between sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-let-go-of-perfectionism&quot;&gt;2. Let go of perfectionism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is normal for hiccups to happen.&lt;strong&gt;A structured plan is important but flexibility is also key.&lt;/strong&gt; If this sounds paradoxical, let me explain further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be unforeseen circumstances. Let’s say your family got into an accident, you won’t be sticking to your gym plan. And there is also something called the holidays. Rather than giving up on your exercise plan because you have been missing out on four days or even weeks, continue from where you stop and keep on going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are embarking on a weight management program, you ought to be giving yourself a huge applaud for taking a conscious step to make changes. The last thing you want to do is to beat yourself out with notions that you are undisciplined and destined to fail. Let go of all of this and take every new opportunity to work towards your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-identify-the-importance-of-weight-loss-in-your-life&quot;&gt;1. Identify the importance of weight loss in your life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the effective ways to encourage people to stay on a weight management program is for them to identify the importance of the weight loss in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been living an unhealthy lifestyle for 20-40 years, you need to find motivation: reasons for you to exercise and eat clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation comes in different forms: extrinsic, intrinsic and a combination of extrinsic and intrinsic.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extrinsic motivation are external factors that motivate you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be advice from doctors and suggestion from the spouse. This form of motivation may encourage you initially but they seldom provide long term motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to also explore the intrinsic motivation of your weight loss, which is your own personal achievement that you can derive from the behavioral change. It can be things like less stress. Lastly, these motivations do not have to be mutually exclusive. You can combine them to motivate yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="weight management program" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">What is the first thing that you think about when people mention weight loss? Many people will conjure up images of deprivation. Not being able to eat the food they like. Endless exercises. Running like a gazelle. Giving up the comfort of their cosy chair. Moving around a place full of self-obsessed people. It is precisely this line of thought that prevents people from starting a weight management program. I did not start out loving the gym. If you were to tell me 5 years ago that I will love hanging out in the gym, I will think that you are crazy. I’m not selling you a castle in the cloud, I’m talking about sustainable changes that will stage you up for success in your weight management program. Today, I’m going to tell you how you could increase your commitment to weight management plan and avoid the pitfall of self-sabotaging behaviors like “I’m not good enough”, “It’s too scary” or “I’m never getting there”. 4. Start easy Do you apply for CEO when you just graduate from school? Changes are you start as an executive on the lower management level. So why is it that when people approach weight loss, they change their diet and exercise from one extreme to the other extreme? After a few days, they start to have cravings and they have to struggle with their willpower. Yes, some people have super willpower to succeed this way. But for one person that succeed, there are many more who will scrap their diet change as a failure and think that there is no point in doing it. It’s much easier to start with small changes and work towards your ultimate goal. If you are just starting out, even eating one healthy meal or exercising once a week is a great start. Once it becomes habitual, you can start increasing the amount of healthy food, cutting the calories and exercising more regularly. 3. Have a structured plan I’m not always a fan of having a structured plan. But over the years, I feel that having a structured plan will reduce my needs to rely on my emotions to make decision. Of course, it is great that if you are feeling motivated and are hitting the gym, exercising regularly and eating clean. But what happen if you are not feeling your very best and decide to skip the gym for one day, and then the next, and then the next? Having a structured plan reduces the guesswork and need to rely on willpower. Make it as specify as possible. If Thursday is your legs day, on Wednesday night, plan out the time you are going to the gym, exact exercises, reps, sets. I will go so far as to even plan the rest time in between sets. 2. Let go of perfectionism It is normal for hiccups to happen.A structured plan is important but flexibility is also key. If this sounds paradoxical, let me explain further. There will be unforeseen circumstances. Let’s say your family got into an accident, you won’t be sticking to your gym plan. And there is also something called the holidays. Rather than giving up on your exercise plan because you have been missing out on four days or even weeks, continue from where you stop and keep on going. When you are embarking on a weight management program, you ought to be giving yourself a huge applaud for taking a conscious step to make changes. The last thing you want to do is to beat yourself out with notions that you are undisciplined and destined to fail. Let go of all of this and take every new opportunity to work towards your goal. 1. Identify the importance of weight loss in your life One of the effective ways to encourage people to stay on a weight management program is for them to identify the importance of the weight loss in their lives. If you have been living an unhealthy lifestyle for 20-40 years, you need to find motivation: reasons for you to exercise and eat clean. Motivation comes in different forms: extrinsic, intrinsic and a combination of extrinsic and intrinsic. Extrinsic motivation are external factors that motivate you. It can be advice from doctors and suggestion from the spouse. This form of motivation may encourage you initially but they seldom provide long term motivation. You want to also explore the intrinsic motivation of your weight loss, which is your own personal achievement that you can derive from the behavioral change. It can be things like less stress. Lastly, these motivations do not have to be mutually exclusive. You can combine them to motivate yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">5 facts about our spine to prevent yoga injuries - Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/06/07/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 facts about our spine to prevent yoga injuries - Part 2" /><published>2015-06-07T15:05:18+08:00</published><updated>2015-06-07T15:05:18+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/06/07/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/06/07/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners-2/">&lt;p&gt;Last week, we introduce you to part 1 of this series: &lt;a href=&quot;/fitness/2015/05/31/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners/&quot;&gt;five facts about our spine to prevent yoga injuries&lt;/a&gt;. We touch on the cervical and thoracic spine, which are the neck and the upper back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, we will move on to explore another 3 exercise sciences that yoga practitioners should know and refer to as a foundation of their practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original intention of yoga is not to perform at cirque du soliel. It should be a practice to maintain a healthy spine, increase awareness and increase positive feelings for the practitioners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the next 3 facts that we should know about our spine in order to prevent injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-our-lumbar-spine-should-be-stable&quot;&gt;3. Our lumbar spine should be stable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lumbar spine consists of five vertebrae, which are the largest vertebrae in the spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary function of the lumbar spine is to bear the weight of the body. To allow support, we need to stiffen the muscles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
While our lumbar spine can rotate, most of the rotation in our activities of daily living should be from the hips and the thoracic spine.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in last week’s article, modern day living lifestyle of prolonged seating posture has changed the way our bodies work. We are constantly in hip flexion and spine flexion, so the muscles on the back of our body: glutes, erector spinae and latissmus dorsi might be in a lengthened state. And a lengthened muscle is a weak muscle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-yoga&quot;&gt;Application to yoga&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have muscles at the back that are lengthened, what could be a good reason to be practicing the yoga asanas that requires forward bend, i.e. stretch the muscles at the back?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might feel good about stretching our lumbar spine in the moment because we perceive relief via the stimulation of the muscle stretch receptors. &lt;strong&gt;The way to ensure a healthy back is to focus on stabilizing our lumbar spine&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually in yoga classes, we are taught to hollow our abdominal, “draw our belly button into the spine”. This movement focus on only the muscles in the front of our body. However, stabilisation of the lumbar spine is most effective when all the muscles around our abdominal are engaged. To do that, we need to move towards bracing our abdominals, creating a much greater degree of stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not saying that you should avoid all flexion activities in yoga. In fact, the cat-camel postures have been one of the exercises recommended by Dr Stuart Mcgill, the leading researcher on spinal health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to seek a balance and mindful approach to yoga. Rather than collapsing into a posture, which very flexible people most certainly could do, we need to engage the muscles to move our spine into a long even curve, distributing the stretch evenly and practice a variety of movements rather than doing lots of forward bend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-frequent-hyperextension-of-the-lumbar-spine-can-cause-damage&quot;&gt;2. Frequent hyperextension of the lumbar spine can cause damage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we mention above, our lumbar spine is supposed to be stable, so naturally, it mean that they are not suppose to be hyperextending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extension of the lumbar spine occurs when we move our spine to a neutral position from a forward bend or when we lean backwards from our netural position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The safe limit of spinal compression is as recommended by National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health is below 3300 Newton (N).
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing exercise/asana that hyperextend your back will put your spinal compression above that safe level will increase the risk of trauma spinal compression. One such exercise or yoga asana that required hyperextension is superman/locust. It places 6000N of stress on the spine, almost twice the safe limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-yoga-1&quot;&gt;Application to yoga&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In yoga, we have many backbending postures. Backbending postures invigorate and allow us to explore our body in interesting ways. &lt;strong&gt;A proper backbend can only be executed if one has sufficient shoulder, upper back and hips flexibility&lt;/strong&gt;. As mentioned in point 3, our lumbar spine should be stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we introduce any deep backbending asanas, we must be certain that we can engage our core muscles in the movements to prevent hyperextension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any point of time, we should not see a sharp change in angle in our back. This can be observed when people try to rely on the hands in upward facing dog or try to go into a deeper arch in Warrior II. It might seem like a deeper stretch, but this will cause compression in the base of the spine, jamming the two vertebrae together. Backbend should never be done by crunching the lower back but instead, it should be done by distributing the bend throughout the spine with engaged core muscles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know the locust pose looks cool, but it might be best to skip it to save your back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1--our-discs-rehydrate-overnight&quot;&gt;1 . Our discs rehydrate overnight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In between two spinal vertebrae, there is a spinal disc. The primary function of the spinal disc is to act as a shock absorber and the inner substance of the disc is made primarily out of water. In order for the disc to function properly, it must be well hydrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we are awake and upright, water is slowly squeezed out of our discs. When sleeping, the unloaded disc will hydrate themselves, which is something that we want to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since the discs have increased their volume, this can make the disc more susceptible to herniation. Disc herniation mainly occurs with excessive or repeated full flexion, e.g. seated forward bend or full standing forward bend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-yoga-2&quot;&gt;Application to yoga&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t we fantasise about the days when the ancient yogis wake up before sun rise to do sun salutations? As yoga practitioners, we try our best to honour the age old tradition, with some common sense. If you want to practice your asanas in the morning, take extra cautious, warm up amply and don’t go into the full expression of the posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember yoga is about the function, not the form.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we sequence a yoga practice for the body, we can reduce the number of spinal flexion. We want to practice yoga intelligently so that it improves your physical and mental well-being. The last thing we want is for yoga to wreck our bodies, which with the wrong repetitive daily practice is not impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And who says yoga is only limited to yoga asanas, you could read a line of sutras or practice mindfulness, that is also a form of yoga practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is to become empowered to use discernment when doing yoga. Just because it is called yoga doesn’t mean it is the right thing for your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;question-the-teachings-and-listen-to-your-body&quot;&gt;Question the teachings and listen to your body.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;REFERENCE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Stuart Mcgill. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.backfitpro.com/documents/Spine-flexion-myths-truths-and-issues.pdf&quot;&gt;Spine flexion exercise: Myths, Truths and Issues affecting health and performance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;backfitpro&lt;/em&gt;.
Professor Stuart Mcgill. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.backfitpro.com/pdf/selecting_back_exercises.pdf&quot;&gt;Designing Back Exercise: from Rehabilitation to Enhancing Performance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;backfitpro&lt;/em&gt;.
Cassie Dionne. &lt;a href=&quot;http://breakingmuscle.com/mobility-recovery/why-your-approach-to-fixing-your-low-back-is-making-it-worse&quot;&gt;Why Your Approach to Fixing Your Low Back Is Making It Worse&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Breaking muscle&lt;/em&gt;.
3 October 2013. Dave. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hybridperspective.com/2013/10/03/bridge-mobility-why-your-gymnasts-may-be-struggling-possible-injury-prevention-for-the-lower-back/&quot;&gt;Bridge Mobility: Why Your Gymnasts May Be Struggling: Possible Injury Prevention For The Lower Back and Tips To Help&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Hybrid Perspective&lt;/em&gt;.
27 October 2011. Dr Lynda Chen. &lt;a href=&quot;https://drlyndachen.wordpress.com/2011/10/27/superman-not-that-super-for-your-spine-read-why/&quot;&gt;Superman – Not That “Super” For Your Spine. READ Why!&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Chiropractic corner with Dr. Chen&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="yoga" /><category term="exercise science" /><summary type="html">Last week, we introduce you to part 1 of this series: five facts about our spine to prevent yoga injuries. We touch on the cervical and thoracic spine, which are the neck and the upper back. This week, we will move on to explore another 3 exercise sciences that yoga practitioners should know and refer to as a foundation of their practice. The original intention of yoga is not to perform at cirque du soliel. It should be a practice to maintain a healthy spine, increase awareness and increase positive feelings for the practitioners. Here are the next 3 facts that we should know about our spine in order to prevent injuries. 3. Our lumbar spine should be stable Our lumbar spine consists of five vertebrae, which are the largest vertebrae in the spine. The primary function of the lumbar spine is to bear the weight of the body. To allow support, we need to stiffen the muscles. While our lumbar spine can rotate, most of the rotation in our activities of daily living should be from the hips and the thoracic spine. As mentioned in last week’s article, modern day living lifestyle of prolonged seating posture has changed the way our bodies work. We are constantly in hip flexion and spine flexion, so the muscles on the back of our body: glutes, erector spinae and latissmus dorsi might be in a lengthened state. And a lengthened muscle is a weak muscle Application to yoga If we have muscles at the back that are lengthened, what could be a good reason to be practicing the yoga asanas that requires forward bend, i.e. stretch the muscles at the back? We might feel good about stretching our lumbar spine in the moment because we perceive relief via the stimulation of the muscle stretch receptors. The way to ensure a healthy back is to focus on stabilizing our lumbar spine. Usually in yoga classes, we are taught to hollow our abdominal, “draw our belly button into the spine”. This movement focus on only the muscles in the front of our body. However, stabilisation of the lumbar spine is most effective when all the muscles around our abdominal are engaged. To do that, we need to move towards bracing our abdominals, creating a much greater degree of stability. We are not saying that you should avoid all flexion activities in yoga. In fact, the cat-camel postures have been one of the exercises recommended by Dr Stuart Mcgill, the leading researcher on spinal health. We need to seek a balance and mindful approach to yoga. Rather than collapsing into a posture, which very flexible people most certainly could do, we need to engage the muscles to move our spine into a long even curve, distributing the stretch evenly and practice a variety of movements rather than doing lots of forward bend. 2. Frequent hyperextension of the lumbar spine can cause damage As we mention above, our lumbar spine is supposed to be stable, so naturally, it mean that they are not suppose to be hyperextending. Extension of the lumbar spine occurs when we move our spine to a neutral position from a forward bend or when we lean backwards from our netural position. The safe limit of spinal compression is as recommended by National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health is below 3300 Newton (N). Doing exercise/asana that hyperextend your back will put your spinal compression above that safe level will increase the risk of trauma spinal compression. One such exercise or yoga asana that required hyperextension is superman/locust. It places 6000N of stress on the spine, almost twice the safe limit. Application to yoga In yoga, we have many backbending postures. Backbending postures invigorate and allow us to explore our body in interesting ways. A proper backbend can only be executed if one has sufficient shoulder, upper back and hips flexibility. As mentioned in point 3, our lumbar spine should be stable. Before we introduce any deep backbending asanas, we must be certain that we can engage our core muscles in the movements to prevent hyperextension. At any point of time, we should not see a sharp change in angle in our back. This can be observed when people try to rely on the hands in upward facing dog or try to go into a deeper arch in Warrior II. It might seem like a deeper stretch, but this will cause compression in the base of the spine, jamming the two vertebrae together. Backbend should never be done by crunching the lower back but instead, it should be done by distributing the bend throughout the spine with engaged core muscles. I know the locust pose looks cool, but it might be best to skip it to save your back. 1 . Our discs rehydrate overnight In between two spinal vertebrae, there is a spinal disc. The primary function of the spinal disc is to act as a shock absorber and the inner substance of the disc is made primarily out of water. In order for the disc to function properly, it must be well hydrated. When we are awake and upright, water is slowly squeezed out of our discs. When sleeping, the unloaded disc will hydrate themselves, which is something that we want to happen. However, since the discs have increased their volume, this can make the disc more susceptible to herniation. Disc herniation mainly occurs with excessive or repeated full flexion, e.g. seated forward bend or full standing forward bend. Application to yoga Don’t we fantasise about the days when the ancient yogis wake up before sun rise to do sun salutations? As yoga practitioners, we try our best to honour the age old tradition, with some common sense. If you want to practice your asanas in the morning, take extra cautious, warm up amply and don’t go into the full expression of the posture. Remember yoga is about the function, not the form. When we sequence a yoga practice for the body, we can reduce the number of spinal flexion. We want to practice yoga intelligently so that it improves your physical and mental well-being. The last thing we want is for yoga to wreck our bodies, which with the wrong repetitive daily practice is not impossible. And who says yoga is only limited to yoga asanas, you could read a line of sutras or practice mindfulness, that is also a form of yoga practice. The bottom line is to become empowered to use discernment when doing yoga. Just because it is called yoga doesn’t mean it is the right thing for your body. Question the teachings and listen to your body. REFERENCE Professor Stuart Mcgill. Spine flexion exercise: Myths, Truths and Issues affecting health and performance. backfitpro. Professor Stuart Mcgill. Designing Back Exercise: from Rehabilitation to Enhancing Performance. backfitpro. Cassie Dionne. Why Your Approach to Fixing Your Low Back Is Making It Worse. Breaking muscle. 3 October 2013. Dave. Bridge Mobility: Why Your Gymnasts May Be Struggling: Possible Injury Prevention For The Lower Back and Tips To Help. The Hybrid Perspective. 27 October 2011. Dr Lynda Chen. Superman – Not That “Super” For Your Spine. READ Why! Chiropractic corner with Dr. Chen</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">5 facts about our spine to prevent yoga injuries - Part 1</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/05/31/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 facts about our spine to prevent yoga injuries - Part 1" /><published>2015-05-31T12:05:05+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-31T12:05:05+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/05/31/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/05/31/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners/">&lt;p&gt;In yoga, there is a saying, “You are Only as Young as your Spine is Flexible”. Yoga benefits include reducing stress, increasing positive emotions and improving our physical body. However, we are also seeing yoga injuries on the rise as yoga has became increasingly athletic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not only until I embark on my journey to become a certified fitness instructor that I realize that there is a huge
gap in my knowledge of the human body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although yoga goes beyond the physical, most practitioners adopt a strong physical practice. So a lack of human anatomy and kinesiology in the yoga teachercould potentially cause injuries to practitioners. We can actually find &lt;a href=&quot;http://loveyogaanatomy.com/what-are-we-actually-doing-in-asana-introducing-the-wawadia-project/&quot;&gt;personal yoga anecdotes&lt;/a&gt; at the What Are We Actually Doing in Asana? Project by Matthew Remski.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, we go into the 5 facts, let’s understand the structure of our spine. Our spine is made up of 4 sections: &lt;strong&gt;cervical spine (neck)&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;thoracic spine (upper back)&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;lumbar spine (lower back)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sacral curve (tail bone)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spine serves as a pillar of support to our body and to protect our spinal cord. Our spines have curves as this structure enables our spines to withstand heavy stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we will look into 5 facts about our spine to create a safe environment for our yoga practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-our-cervical-spine-is-the-weakest-part-of-the-entire-spine&quot;&gt;5. Our cervical spine is the weakest part of the entire spine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start from the top, our cervical spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyday, our cervical spine has to support our head, which is about 4.5 to 5 kg. Nowadays, due to modern day lifestyle, we are already putting a lot of stress on our cervical spine. A head forward-tilt position adds pressure to our cervical spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
A 15 degrees put 12 kg and 60 degrees tilt put 27kg of stress on the cervical spine¹.
&lt;br /&gt;
Every inch of forward head posture is putting at least 3 kg of stress on the cervical spine².
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, this amount of daily stress put into our cervical spine might cause a loss of the natural curve, wear, tear, early degeneration and weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-yoga&quot;&gt;Application to yoga&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In yoga, the headstand and shoulder stand has been touted as the king and queen of yoga practice. In additional, there is the plough pose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we go into these postures, we are placing tremendous stress on our cervical spine, which has been most probably weakened by modern day living. There are both benefits and risks to inversions. We should only attempt these postures after careful evaluation of the strength of the cervical spine and the risks-benefits involve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When going into the postures, care must be taken to transfer the weight of the body away from the cervical spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;headstand&lt;/strong&gt;, we have to learn to use our shoulders and arms to support our weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;shoulder stand&lt;/strong&gt;, we can increase the surface area of the back in contact with the floor or use a blanket to reduce the flexion of the neck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will skip the &lt;strong&gt;plough&lt;/strong&gt; because I don’t think they are worth it. But the decision is yours to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-our-thoracic-spine-should-be-mobile&quot;&gt;4. Our thoracic spine should be mobile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thoracic mobility is essential for maintaining a good posture in our daily living. A stiff thoracic spine can be inferred from an increased in the rounding of upper back, a forward head posture and possibly an increase in the lower back curve. Again, our modern day lifestyle of constant sitting can lead to this negative change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stiff thoracic restrict the ribs joint, which in turn restrict breathing. Our bodies never work in isolation, when one region is out of balance, it will affect the other region. In the case of stiffness of the thoracic spine, the lumbar spine will come into the picture to take the role of the thoracic spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the thoracic spine has failed to do what it is supposed to do. So, the lumbar spine has to take on the function that it is not design to be doing in order to compensate for this failure. In such event, the lumbar spine will become overwork, possibly resulting in lower back pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-yoga-1&quot;&gt;Application to yoga&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoga is about connecting the body and the mind through the breath. So an inability to breathe deeply will reduce the calming benefits of yoga practice. There are a lot of twisting postures in yoga. In order to gain an optimal functionality of our body in the practice, we should feel the rotation more in our thoracic spine than the lumbar spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we complain about lower back pain or neck, the source of pain might be coming from the thoracic spine. Rather than doing more neck or lower back exercises, we should spend some time considering the kinetic link and look into our thoracic spine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to get to the root of the problem in order to implement a long term solution. However, do note that it is outside the scope of yoga to diagnose the cause of problems and we should be looking for accredited professionals if required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week, we will cover &lt;a href=&quot;/fitness/2015/06/07/5-spine-facts-for-yoga-practitioners-2/&quot;&gt;3 more facts&lt;/a&gt; about the spine for a more well-informed yoga practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;REFERENCE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¹18 November 2014. Madlen Davies. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-2839455/Why-hunching-phone-gives-pain-Image-shows-tilting-head-puts-four-STONE-extra-pressure-neck.html&quot;&gt;Have YOU got text neck? How hunching over your phone puts 60lbs of extra pressure on the spine&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Mail Online&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;²Erik Dalton. &lt;a href=&quot;http://erikdalton.com/media/published-articles/forward-head-posture/&quot;&gt;Forward Head Posture&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Dalton Myoskeletal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4 February 2014. Ryan Wagner. &lt;a href=&quot;http://motusfitness.com/why-you-should-care-about-thoracic-spine-mobility/&quot;&gt;Why you should care about thoracic spine mobility&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Motus Fitness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14 January 2012. Joanna Walters. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2012/jan/14/yoga-can-damage-body-row&quot;&gt;‘Yoga can damage your body’ article throws exponents off-balance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Guardian&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="yoga" /><category term="exercise science" /><summary type="html">In yoga, there is a saying, “You are Only as Young as your Spine is Flexible”. Yoga benefits include reducing stress, increasing positive emotions and improving our physical body. However, we are also seeing yoga injuries on the rise as yoga has became increasingly athletic. It is not only until I embark on my journey to become a certified fitness instructor that I realize that there is a huge gap in my knowledge of the human body. Although yoga goes beyond the physical, most practitioners adopt a strong physical practice. So a lack of human anatomy and kinesiology in the yoga teachercould potentially cause injuries to practitioners. We can actually find personal yoga anecdotes at the What Are We Actually Doing in Asana? Project by Matthew Remski. Before, we go into the 5 facts, let’s understand the structure of our spine. Our spine is made up of 4 sections: cervical spine (neck), thoracic spine (upper back), lumbar spine (lower back) and sacral curve (tail bone). The spine serves as a pillar of support to our body and to protect our spinal cord. Our spines have curves as this structure enables our spines to withstand heavy stress. Today, we will look into 5 facts about our spine to create a safe environment for our yoga practices. 5. Our cervical spine is the weakest part of the entire spine Let’s start from the top, our cervical spine. Everyday, our cervical spine has to support our head, which is about 4.5 to 5 kg. Nowadays, due to modern day lifestyle, we are already putting a lot of stress on our cervical spine. A head forward-tilt position adds pressure to our cervical spine. A 15 degrees put 12 kg and 60 degrees tilt put 27kg of stress on the cervical spine¹. Every inch of forward head posture is putting at least 3 kg of stress on the cervical spine². Over time, this amount of daily stress put into our cervical spine might cause a loss of the natural curve, wear, tear, early degeneration and weakness. Application to yoga In yoga, the headstand and shoulder stand has been touted as the king and queen of yoga practice. In additional, there is the plough pose. When we go into these postures, we are placing tremendous stress on our cervical spine, which has been most probably weakened by modern day living. There are both benefits and risks to inversions. We should only attempt these postures after careful evaluation of the strength of the cervical spine and the risks-benefits involve. When going into the postures, care must be taken to transfer the weight of the body away from the cervical spine. In headstand, we have to learn to use our shoulders and arms to support our weight. In shoulder stand, we can increase the surface area of the back in contact with the floor or use a blanket to reduce the flexion of the neck. I will skip the plough because I don’t think they are worth it. But the decision is yours to make. 4. Our thoracic spine should be mobile Thoracic mobility is essential for maintaining a good posture in our daily living. A stiff thoracic spine can be inferred from an increased in the rounding of upper back, a forward head posture and possibly an increase in the lower back curve. Again, our modern day lifestyle of constant sitting can lead to this negative change. A stiff thoracic restrict the ribs joint, which in turn restrict breathing. Our bodies never work in isolation, when one region is out of balance, it will affect the other region. In the case of stiffness of the thoracic spine, the lumbar spine will come into the picture to take the role of the thoracic spine. In other words, the thoracic spine has failed to do what it is supposed to do. So, the lumbar spine has to take on the function that it is not design to be doing in order to compensate for this failure. In such event, the lumbar spine will become overwork, possibly resulting in lower back pain. Application to yoga Yoga is about connecting the body and the mind through the breath. So an inability to breathe deeply will reduce the calming benefits of yoga practice. There are a lot of twisting postures in yoga. In order to gain an optimal functionality of our body in the practice, we should feel the rotation more in our thoracic spine than the lumbar spine. When we complain about lower back pain or neck, the source of pain might be coming from the thoracic spine. Rather than doing more neck or lower back exercises, we should spend some time considering the kinetic link and look into our thoracic spine. We have to get to the root of the problem in order to implement a long term solution. However, do note that it is outside the scope of yoga to diagnose the cause of problems and we should be looking for accredited professionals if required. Next week, we will cover 3 more facts about the spine for a more well-informed yoga practice. REFERENCE ¹18 November 2014. Madlen Davies. Have YOU got text neck? How hunching over your phone puts 60lbs of extra pressure on the spine. Mail Online. ²Erik Dalton. Forward Head Posture. Dalton Myoskeletal. 4 February 2014. Ryan Wagner. Why you should care about thoracic spine mobility. Motus Fitness. 14 January 2012. Joanna Walters. ‘Yoga can damage your body’ article throws exponents off-balance. The Guardian.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3 exercise science that all yoga practitioners should know</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/05/24/3-exercise-science-for-yoga-practitioners/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 exercise science that all yoga practitioners should know" /><published>2015-05-24T16:23:52+08:00</published><updated>2015-05-24T16:23:52+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/05/24/3-exercise-science-for-yoga-practitioners</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/fitness/2015/05/24/3-exercise-science-for-yoga-practitioners/">&lt;p&gt;Yoga can be spiritual, physical and/or mental exercise for the practitioners. Some practitioners do mostly pranayama. Some like hand balances and strong posture. Some do raja yoga, the yoga of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of yoga is that there is a variety of practices that appeals to people of different personalities and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But generally, most people know yoga as a physical practice. The practice of &lt;em&gt;asanas&lt;/em&gt;, the physical postures, is a form of physical exercise. Even though yoga is considered to be of low impact, you still can get hurt (read: &lt;strong&gt;sports injuries&lt;/strong&gt;) if you don’t practice it with the right knowledge and mindfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-exercise-science&quot;&gt;Enter exercise science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, yoga is a great movement-based activity to engage it. It helps one to focus, reduce stress, build strength and many more. We could gain more benefits from yoga if we educate ourselves on these 3 exercise science.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevent injuries and optimize the practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-stretching-is-not-a-warm-up&quot;&gt;3. Stretching is not a warm up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my younger days, warming up means static stretching, the kind that you hold the stretch for seconds. But science has proven that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/777155&quot;&gt;static stretching as a warm up decreases muscular strength and power&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A warm up should preferably be a dynamic activity that gradually increases the body internal temperature and prepares the body for more rigorous demands of the session. It should be a combination of light aerobic exercises and active stretches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t stretch a cold muscle.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoga classes should never start with static stretches. When you do static stretches before exercising, your body may think it’s at risk of being overstretched. It compensates by contracting and becoming more tense. That means you aren’t able to move as fast or as freely, making you more likely to get hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-stretch-properly&quot;&gt;2. Stretch properly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yoga is not only about stretching, but since it is what comes into people mind when they first think about stretching, we will continue to talk a little more about the science of stretching. Never do a ballistic stretch, that is bouncing while you stretch. By attempting to use the momentum to stretch further, you are not allowing your muscles to adjust to the stretch and can cause injuries. Also, ballistic stretching activates the &lt;a href=&quot;http://people.bath.ac.uk/masrjb/Stretch/stretching_2.html#SEC15&quot;&gt;stretch reflex&lt;/a&gt;, causing the muscles to contract, thus defeating the purpose of stretching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stretch correctly, move to a point where you feel tension in your muscles without discomfort, avoid pain and hold the stretch for 15 to 60 seconds with two to four repetitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-some-postures-can-be-a-little-too-extreme-to-your-hips&quot;&gt;3. Some postures can be a little too extreme to your hips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t we just adore the picture of yogis in the extreme backbends and extreme forward bends? Don’t we just wish that we are as bendy as them? It seems to me that images that inspired people to practice yoga are people with flexibilities that can qualify them into cirque du soleil. Unless we are really part of the entertainment company, there is no valid reason for most of us to work towards some extreme postures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in such extreme postures could cause damage to our hips joints. Our hips are ball and socket joint and this kind of joint allows a large range of motion. When we move jam our thigh bone into our hips: forward bending, splits, putting our legs behind our head, it will create friction in the hips joint. If we happen to have &lt;a href=&quot;http://orthoinfo.aaos.org/topic.cfm?topic=A00571&quot;&gt;femoroacetabular impingement&lt;/a&gt; (FAI) forms, the femoral head will rub abnormally against the acetabulum, creating addition friction, which will potentially create damage to the hip joint. FAI can cause pain in the hips area and it is also associated with cartilage damage, labral tears, early hip arthritis, sports hernias, and low back pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Respect the limits of your body, stay away from pain and drop your ego and competitiveness in a yoga practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are some of the exercise science that you think yogis should equip themselves with? &lt;strong&gt;Share with us in the comment section below.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;REFERENCE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;16 Apr 2010. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/active/7594484/Stretching-before-exercise-is-counter-productive.html&quot;&gt;Stretching before exercise ‘is counter-productive’&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Telegraph.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brad. &lt;a href=&quot;http://stretchcoach.com/articles/myotatic-stretch-reflex/&quot;&gt;Understanding the Stretch Reflex (or Myotatic Reflex)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Stretch Coach.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 Nov 2005. J. R. Crawford, R. N. Villar. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bjj.boneandjoint.org.uk/content/87-B/11/1459.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Current concepts in the management of femoroacetabular impingement&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hipfai.com/&quot;&gt;Femoroacetabular Impingement (FAI)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Orth Enterprises.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 Apr 2014. Joe Miller. &lt;a href=&quot;http://joemilleryoga.com/glutes-hip-pain-yoga/&quot;&gt;The glutes and hip pain in yoga&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Joe Miller.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26 Nov 2016. Sheryl Ubelacker. &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.nationalpost.com/health/yoga-regimens-and-poses-pushed-too-far-can-lead-to-hip-injuries-osteoarthritis-sports-mds&quot;&gt;Yoga regimens and poses pushed too far can lead to hip injuries, even osteoarthritis, sports MDs say&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;The Canadian Press.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="yoga" /><category term="exercise science" /><summary type="html">Yoga can be spiritual, physical and/or mental exercise for the practitioners. Some practitioners do mostly pranayama. Some like hand balances and strong posture. Some do raja yoga, the yoga of meditation. The beauty of yoga is that there is a variety of practices that appeals to people of different personalities and needs. But generally, most people know yoga as a physical practice. The practice of asanas, the physical postures, is a form of physical exercise. Even though yoga is considered to be of low impact, you still can get hurt (read: sports injuries) if you don’t practice it with the right knowledge and mindfulness. Enter exercise science Having said that, yoga is a great movement-based activity to engage it. It helps one to focus, reduce stress, build strength and many more. We could gain more benefits from yoga if we educate ourselves on these 3 exercise science.   Prevent injuries and optimize the practice. 3. Stretching is not a warm up In my younger days, warming up means static stretching, the kind that you hold the stretch for seconds. But science has proven that static stretching as a warm up decreases muscular strength and power. A warm up should preferably be a dynamic activity that gradually increases the body internal temperature and prepares the body for more rigorous demands of the session. It should be a combination of light aerobic exercises and active stretches. Don’t stretch a cold muscle. Yoga classes should never start with static stretches. When you do static stretches before exercising, your body may think it’s at risk of being overstretched. It compensates by contracting and becoming more tense. That means you aren’t able to move as fast or as freely, making you more likely to get hurt. 2. Stretch properly Yoga is not only about stretching, but since it is what comes into people mind when they first think about stretching, we will continue to talk a little more about the science of stretching. Never do a ballistic stretch, that is bouncing while you stretch. By attempting to use the momentum to stretch further, you are not allowing your muscles to adjust to the stretch and can cause injuries. Also, ballistic stretching activates the stretch reflex, causing the muscles to contract, thus defeating the purpose of stretching. To stretch correctly, move to a point where you feel tension in your muscles without discomfort, avoid pain and hold the stretch for 15 to 60 seconds with two to four repetitions. 3. Some postures can be a little too extreme to your hips Don’t we just adore the picture of yogis in the extreme backbends and extreme forward bends? Don’t we just wish that we are as bendy as them? It seems to me that images that inspired people to practice yoga are people with flexibilities that can qualify them into cirque du soleil. Unless we are really part of the entertainment company, there is no valid reason for most of us to work towards some extreme postures. Working in such extreme postures could cause damage to our hips joints. Our hips are ball and socket joint and this kind of joint allows a large range of motion. When we move jam our thigh bone into our hips: forward bending, splits, putting our legs behind our head, it will create friction in the hips joint. If we happen to have femoroacetabular impingement (FAI) forms, the femoral head will rub abnormally against the acetabulum, creating addition friction, which will potentially create damage to the hip joint. FAI can cause pain in the hips area and it is also associated with cartilage damage, labral tears, early hip arthritis, sports hernias, and low back pain. Respect the limits of your body, stay away from pain and drop your ego and competitiveness in a yoga practice. What are some of the exercise science that you think yogis should equip themselves with? Share with us in the comment section below. REFERENCE 16 Apr 2010. Stretching before exercise ‘is counter-productive’. The Telegraph. Brad. Understanding the Stretch Reflex (or Myotatic Reflex). Stretch Coach. 11 Nov 2005. J. R. Crawford, R. N. Villar. Current concepts in the management of femoroacetabular impingement. The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery. Femoroacetabular Impingement (FAI). Orth Enterprises. 11 Apr 2014. Joe Miller. The glutes and hip pain in yoga. Joe Miller. 26 Nov 2016. Sheryl Ubelacker. Yoga regimens and poses pushed too far can lead to hip injuries, even osteoarthritis, sports MDs say. The Canadian Press.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">5 yoga techniques to manage your stress in 5 minutes: Part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal%20development/2015/04/05/manage-stress-in-5-mins-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="5 yoga techniques to manage your stress in 5 minutes: Part 2" /><published>2015-04-05T14:22:16+08:00</published><updated>2015-04-05T14:22:16+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal%20development/2015/04/05/manage-stress-in-5-mins-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal%20development/2015/04/05/manage-stress-in-5-mins-2/">&lt;p&gt;Last week, we talk about &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/03/25/manage-stress-in-5-mins/&quot;&gt;2 techniques&lt;/a&gt; to relieve stress using physical movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand that you probably can’t apply those when you are working without getting unnecessary attention. Today, we are going to finish this 2 part series so with tools that you can cope with your stress anywhere anytime. You can apply these techniques in a public transport, workplace, restroom and restaurant without anybody knowing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-breathe-deeply&quot;&gt;3. Breathe deeply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we mention last week, our breath and emotion are intricately connection. To do a quick recap, fast and short breathing are associated with restlessness and strong emotions like shock and anger. On the other hand, deep and slow breathing are associated with relaxation. Here are 2 ways to make breathing into a stress relieving activity in 5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-1&quot;&gt;Method 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on your breath, make it deep, gentle and smooth. When you feel that your mind is wandering away from the breath, gently bring it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-2&quot;&gt;Method 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inhale, count your inhalation. Exhale, count your exhalation. Inhale, count your inhalation. Exhale, this time round make the count of your exhalation double the count of inhalation. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-engage-in-light-mindfulness-activity&quot;&gt;4. Engage in light mindfulness activity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to meditate to be practicing mindfulness. In fact, mindfulness should be a practice that you can engage in anytime. Preferably, you should be applying mindfulness to your every waking moment. Practicing is as simple as being aware of what you is around you right at this moment. Every minute is an opportunity for you to practice awareness. Here is one example each for practicing mindfulness at home and at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;home&quot;&gt;Home&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When doing mundane house chore, it is easy for your mind to be filled with thoughts. Instead of rushing to finish the chore, take 5 minutes to tap into your inner well of awareness by becoming present in whatever you are holding on or doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say you are washing dishes, become aware of the weight, color and size of the dishes. Next, turn your awareness to the lather that is produced by the detergent. Notice the color, the volume and the feeling of the foam. Turn your awareness into the water that rinse the dishes clean. Notice the temperature and how it runs down the dishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this, you will be gradually building up your mindfulness “muscles”, and it will be applied more smoothly into your life when a difficult moment arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;work&quot;&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you have met with a difficult problem in your project. Our tendency is to work even harder at the problem and squeeze our brain dry. While this might work for some situations, we might get a better result if we have the courage to momentarily let go of the problem in our mind and return to it with a fresh mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pareto’s Principle states that 80% of our results are derived by 20% of our efforts. So take the courage to let go of the notion that being busy is being productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, it is more practical, productive and better for your well-being to take 5 minutes off your work to apply the mindfulness practice described above (at home) to any of your surrounding at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-tune-in-to-your-current-state-and-release-tension&quot;&gt;5. Tune in to your current state and release tension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers in Finland map bodily sensations associated with different emotions¹. Last week, we talk about how stress triggers a chain of “fight-or-flight” reactions in our body. This week, we will add muscle tensions to the reactions. With this understanding, we will be engaging our physical body as a tool to access our mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, scan your body for muscle tensions. Due to our sedentary lifestyle, this will usually be, but not limited to, shoulders, neck and lower back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, introduce some movements, rotation, extension or flexion to the tense region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus on progressively releasing the tension on the muscles. Alternatively, you can deliberately tense up your muscles and releases them. Focus on the relaxation sensation and breathe deeply to further release your muscle tension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my 5 techniques to manage your stress in 5 minutes. &lt;strong&gt;Do you have any other techniques that you use to release your stress in 5 minutes?&lt;/strong&gt; Let us know in the comment section below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;REFERENCE&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¹27 November 2013. Riitta Hari.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/111/2/646.full&quot;&gt;Bodily maps of emotions.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;PNAS, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="balanced living" /><category term="yoga" /><category term="emotional health" /><summary type="html">Last week, we talk about 2 techniques to relieve stress using physical movements. We understand that you probably can’t apply those when you are working without getting unnecessary attention. Today, we are going to finish this 2 part series so with tools that you can cope with your stress anywhere anytime. You can apply these techniques in a public transport, workplace, restroom and restaurant without anybody knowing it. 3. Breathe deeply As we mention last week, our breath and emotion are intricately connection. To do a quick recap, fast and short breathing are associated with restlessness and strong emotions like shock and anger. On the other hand, deep and slow breathing are associated with relaxation. Here are 2 ways to make breathing into a stress relieving activity in 5 minutes. Method 1 Focus on your breath, make it deep, gentle and smooth. When you feel that your mind is wandering away from the breath, gently bring it back. Method 2 Inhale, count your inhalation. Exhale, count your exhalation. Inhale, count your inhalation. Exhale, this time round make the count of your exhalation double the count of inhalation. Repeat. 4. Engage in light mindfulness activity You don’t have to meditate to be practicing mindfulness. In fact, mindfulness should be a practice that you can engage in anytime. Preferably, you should be applying mindfulness to your every waking moment. Practicing is as simple as being aware of what you is around you right at this moment. Every minute is an opportunity for you to practice awareness. Here is one example each for practicing mindfulness at home and at work. Home When doing mundane house chore, it is easy for your mind to be filled with thoughts. Instead of rushing to finish the chore, take 5 minutes to tap into your inner well of awareness by becoming present in whatever you are holding on or doing. Say you are washing dishes, become aware of the weight, color and size of the dishes. Next, turn your awareness to the lather that is produced by the detergent. Notice the color, the volume and the feeling of the foam. Turn your awareness into the water that rinse the dishes clean. Notice the temperature and how it runs down the dishes. By doing this, you will be gradually building up your mindfulness “muscles”, and it will be applied more smoothly into your life when a difficult moment arises. Work Say you have met with a difficult problem in your project. Our tendency is to work even harder at the problem and squeeze our brain dry. While this might work for some situations, we might get a better result if we have the courage to momentarily let go of the problem in our mind and return to it with a fresh mind. The Pareto’s Principle states that 80% of our results are derived by 20% of our efforts. So take the courage to let go of the notion that being busy is being productive. Sometimes, it is more practical, productive and better for your well-being to take 5 minutes off your work to apply the mindfulness practice described above (at home) to any of your surrounding at work. 5. Tune in to your current state and release tension Researchers in Finland map bodily sensations associated with different emotions¹. Last week, we talk about how stress triggers a chain of “fight-or-flight” reactions in our body. This week, we will add muscle tensions to the reactions. With this understanding, we will be engaging our physical body as a tool to access our mind. First, scan your body for muscle tensions. Due to our sedentary lifestyle, this will usually be, but not limited to, shoulders, neck and lower back. Next, introduce some movements, rotation, extension or flexion to the tense region. Focus on progressively releasing the tension on the muscles. Alternatively, you can deliberately tense up your muscles and releases them. Focus on the relaxation sensation and breathe deeply to further release your muscle tension. Here are my 5 techniques to manage your stress in 5 minutes. Do you have any other techniques that you use to release your stress in 5 minutes? Let us know in the comment section below. REFERENCE ¹27 November 2013. Riitta Hari. Bodily maps of emotions. PNAS, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</summary></entry></feed>