<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.5.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="thegeekwing.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="thegeekwing.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-03T10:46:55+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/</id><title type="html">The Geek Wing</title><subtitle>Hacking through life. Your geeky source for technology, fitness and personal development.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">This blog is now on Jekyll</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/technology/2017/08/02/this-blog-is-now-on-jekyll/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This blog is now on Jekyll" /><published>2017-08-02T22:14:01+08:00</published><updated>2017-08-02T22:14:01+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/technology/2017/08/02/this-blog-is-now-on-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/technology/2017/08/02/this-blog-is-now-on-jekyll/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;wordpress&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using Wordpress hosted on Hostgator for at least 6 years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first started blogging, it is a quick and convenient tool for me to get my website up quickly. Want a new website? Sure, within 15 minutes with a few clicks, a wordpress website is up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the time when I am not coding much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heck, at that point of time, I think CSS and HTML is programming.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I start to delve more into proper programming, front-end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learn about SSH, compile SASS, craft javascript syntax and enroll myself into FreeCodeCamp. Then, I learn about GitHub. It takes me at least a week to figure out what all this Git is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first start to use GitHub, I only think it sounds really cool and geeky. I didn’t understand why is it so useful to developers. Like, isn’t it just a cloud-based platform for people to store code?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I am not impressed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is all this pull, fetch, push, merge about? Why did the GUI tells me that I can’t push the changes to other people code? What exactly is happening? I mean, what is this push for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great, another source of confusion in my already complicated learning journey. I don’t even get why the element of getElementById can have so many more different functions than getElementsByClassName.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Completely lost and hopeless in this coding province.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-hacking&quot;&gt;Keep hacking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days of pressing buttons, reading articles and testing all this different command on my Git Bash. I finally get it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repository and version control.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I crack the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub is a repository for storing your coding files. And it offers version control, which means that if I screw up my code and I want to go back to a previous version of my file, I could just navigate around GitHub and retrieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s like a save in a game, in which, if you die, you can go back to your healthy state!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fall in love and attempt to push all my existing projects to GitHub. There isn’t too many projects at the moment, so I break one website into a few smaller projects. For example, my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wing-puah/tab-navigation&quot;&gt;tabbed navigation with vanilla javascript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just when I think I reach coding heaven, looking at my puny code on this developer hub, shareable and searchable, I found Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You mean something can get more awesome than GitHub?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;static-site-generator&quot;&gt;Static site generator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I mention free hosting on GitHub pages?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogging like a hacker?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing post not through a user interface but on a text editor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving away from the overkilled content management system to a version controlled site pure static HTML files?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Sign me up.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I migrated my blog from Wordpress to Jekyll and I love the transition thus far. It gets me excited that I have complete control over my code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, me. Control freak.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll makes blogging a true state of art.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="blogging" /><category term="wordpress" /><summary type="html">Wordpress I have been using Wordpress hosted on Hostgator for at least 6 years now. When I first started blogging, it is a quick and convenient tool for me to get my website up quickly. Want a new website? Sure, within 15 minutes with a few clicks, a wordpress website is up. That is the time when I am not coding much. Heck, at that point of time, I think CSS and HTML is programming. Last year, I start to delve more into proper programming, front-end. I learn about SSH, compile SASS, craft javascript syntax and enroll myself into FreeCodeCamp. Then, I learn about GitHub. It takes me at least a week to figure out what all this Git is about. Github When I first start to use GitHub, I only think it sounds really cool and geeky. I didn’t understand why is it so useful to developers. Like, isn’t it just a cloud-based platform for people to store code? I am not impressed. And what is all this pull, fetch, push, merge about? Why did the GUI tells me that I can’t push the changes to other people code? What exactly is happening? I mean, what is this push for? Great, another source of confusion in my already complicated learning journey. I don’t even get why the element of getElementById can have so many more different functions than getElementsByClassName. Completely lost and hopeless in this coding province. Keep hacking A few days of pressing buttons, reading articles and testing all this different command on my Git Bash. I finally get it! Repository and version control. I crack the code. GitHub is a repository for storing your coding files. And it offers version control, which means that if I screw up my code and I want to go back to a previous version of my file, I could just navigate around GitHub and retrieve it. It’s like a save in a game, in which, if you die, you can go back to your healthy state! Jekyll I fall in love and attempt to push all my existing projects to GitHub. There isn’t too many projects at the moment, so I break one website into a few smaller projects. For example, my tabbed navigation with vanilla javascript. Just when I think I reach coding heaven, looking at my puny code on this developer hub, shareable and searchable, I found Jekyll. You mean something can get more awesome than GitHub? Static site generator Did I mention free hosting on GitHub pages? Blogging like a hacker? Writing post not through a user interface but on a text editor? Moving away from the overkilled content management system to a version controlled site pure static HTML files? Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Sign me up. I migrated my blog from Wordpress to Jekyll and I love the transition thus far. It gets me excited that I have complete control over my code. Yes, me. Control freak. Jekyll makes blogging a true state of art.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A letter to myself in my early 20s. What will yours look like?</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/musings/2017/03/26/a-letter-to-myself-in-my-early-twenties/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A letter to myself in my early 20s. What will yours look like?" /><published>2017-03-26T14:56:21+08:00</published><updated>2017-03-26T14:56:21+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/musings/2017/03/26/a-letter-to-myself-in-my-early-twenties</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/musings/2017/03/26/a-letter-to-myself-in-my-early-twenties/">&lt;p&gt;Do you take the time to reflect on your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you could write a letter to yourself when you are younger, say in your early 20s, what will you say to yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people will encourage you to enjoy the present or to work towards the future. However, looking back at how far you have traveled, will sometimes fuel you with the drive as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once, I’ve written a letter for myself when I’m &lt;a href=&quot;/musings/2015/12/05/a-motivational-read-for-25-year-old/&quot;&gt;25&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is a letter for me in my early 20s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-wing-in-her-early-20s&quot;&gt;To Wing in her early 20s,&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times, you will feel frustrated with the lack of progress in your life. But there will too be times when you are driven with the notion of invincibility, achieving what most couldn’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you are different. Yes, you never try to shun from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout your early 20s, you will have to bear the judgement of others. But I assure you that you will survive to be stronger. And you will definitely live life in your own terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m in your late 20s, that’s about 2500+ days older than you are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-early-twenties-will-be-an-incredible-journey&quot;&gt;Your early twenties will be an incredible journey.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, you will be living your dream. And there will be a lifetime of stories waiting for you to experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late 20s for you, as I am now, will hold stability, maybe much to your surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the year when you say that if you didn’t achieve what you set to achieve by 25, you will go to the path which many are? Well, you didn’t really reach where you foresee yourself, but neither did you embark on the conventional. But it is okay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-back-i-admire-you-for-your-passion-grit-and-determination&quot;&gt;Looking back, I admire you for your passion, grit and determination.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many things that you shouldn’t do. But you will do it anyway. To be honest, life is still a mystery to me. What they feed you on, the linear route has never aligned its path to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many things that I wish I could correct you in your path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things like not to trust people so easily. To shun situations when you detect bullshit. To be able to discern a little better. To be a little more humble and to think a little further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of what you will be going through, you will grow into a better person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;you-have-to-choose-to-be-better&quot;&gt;You have to choose to be better.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a wave that hits the beach again and again. Born and rebirth. Born and rebirth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will hold many dreams, you will test the limit of many things. You will realise that you will embark on things that will be time waster. You will soon to see that not all dreams are worth pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be choices that might initially look valuable and strategic but are in reality, are distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is okay, because you are young, still in your early 20s, without much to commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then again, even here, in my late twenties, I am still carving out my legacy bit by bit. You will never know what the future brings unless you embark on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;go-forth-with-youradventure&quot;&gt;Go forth with your adventure.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if there is one thing that I will want you to change, is perhaps to stay focus. Regardless of what other say, keep your eyes on your initial goal, that is to help others. Be careful not to fall into the allure of the glit and all that shimmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life hold a mystery for you to discover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, you are a gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your naivety. Thank you for your tenacious spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be the story which we will write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;because-this-is-our-destiny&quot;&gt;Because this is our destiny.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><category term="live your dream" /><category term="passion" /><summary type="html">Do you take the time to reflect on your life? If you could write a letter to yourself when you are younger, say in your early 20s, what will you say to yourself? Many people will encourage you to enjoy the present or to work towards the future. However, looking back at how far you have traveled, will sometimes fuel you with the drive as well. Once, I’ve written a letter for myself when I’m 25. Now, this is a letter for me in my early 20s. To Wing in her early 20s, Many times, you will feel frustrated with the lack of progress in your life. But there will too be times when you are driven with the notion of invincibility, achieving what most couldn’t have. Yes, you are different. Yes, you never try to shun from that. Throughout your early 20s, you will have to bear the judgement of others. But I assure you that you will survive to be stronger. And you will definitely live life in your own terms. Now, I’m in your late 20s, that’s about 2500+ days older than you are now. Your early twenties will be an incredible journey. Yes, you will be living your dream. And there will be a lifetime of stories waiting for you to experience. Late 20s for you, as I am now, will hold stability, maybe much to your surprise. Remember the year when you say that if you didn’t achieve what you set to achieve by 25, you will go to the path which many are? Well, you didn’t really reach where you foresee yourself, but neither did you embark on the conventional. But it is okay. Looking back, I admire you for your passion, grit and determination. There are many things that you shouldn’t do. But you will do it anyway. To be honest, life is still a mystery to me. What they feed you on, the linear route has never aligned its path to you. There are many things that I wish I could correct you in your path. Things like not to trust people so easily. To shun situations when you detect bullshit. To be able to discern a little better. To be a little more humble and to think a little further. Regardless of what you will be going through, you will grow into a better person. You have to choose to be better. Like a wave that hits the beach again and again. Born and rebirth. Born and rebirth. You will hold many dreams, you will test the limit of many things. You will realise that you will embark on things that will be time waster. You will soon to see that not all dreams are worth pursuing. There will be choices that might initially look valuable and strategic but are in reality, are distractions. But it is okay, because you are young, still in your early 20s, without much to commit. Then again, even here, in my late twenties, I am still carving out my legacy bit by bit. You will never know what the future brings unless you embark on it. Go forth with your adventure. However, if there is one thing that I will want you to change, is perhaps to stay focus. Regardless of what other say, keep your eyes on your initial goal, that is to help others. Be careful not to fall into the allure of the glit and all that shimmers. Life hold a mystery for you to discover. And yes, you are a gem. Thank you for your naivety. Thank you for your tenacious spirit. This will be the story which we will write. Because this is our destiny.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">11 ways weight lifting will save your life</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/07/14/11-ways-weight-lifting-will-change-your-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11 ways weight lifting will save your life" /><published>2016-07-14T22:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-07-14T22:54:35+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/07/14/11-ways-weight-lifting-will-change-your-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/07/14/11-ways-weight-lifting-will-change-your-life/">&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting saves my life. It is not merely about what happen in the gym. It is also about the transformation that occurs in my life. Besides looking better, I gain confidence, become more focus and achieve more in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting has that power. Here are &lt;strong&gt;11 ways&lt;/strong&gt; that weight lifting changes your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-youll-look-great&quot;&gt;11. You’ll look great&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lifting weights help you to get lean and toned. You get the healthy shape you are looking for. Cardio might slim you down but you will never achieve that athletic look without implementing resistance training in your life. Ladies, do not worry about getting bulky, it takes a specific hypertrophy program and nutritional plan to gain mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10. Get stronger mentally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you get stronger physically, you will get stronger mentally. Often times, weight lifting requires you to persevere and push yourself to overcome the mental barriers and physical discomfort. It is about moving out of your comfort zone into your uncomfortable zone. If you repeat this simple act for enough time, you will expand your comfort zone. And that is how success happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-prevent-osteoporosis&quot;&gt;9. Prevent osteoporosis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Osteoporosis is a thinning of bone when the formation of new bone is slower than the depletion of bone. Therefore, the bones become brittle and are more prone to fracture. Weight lifting over a period of time can prevent bone loss and even increase bone density.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-improve-balance&quot;&gt;8. Improve balance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our core is the key to maintaining our balance. You need to activate your core during weight lifting, especially single leg exercises or asymmetrical exercises, to maintain your balance and posture. Through weight lifting, you get stronger in your core muscles and improve your balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-lose-fats&quot;&gt;7. Lose fats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting maintains/builds muscles, increases resting metabolic rate and improves insulin resistance, which are important factors in fat loss. When you only use cardio to manage your weight, you tend to lose fats and muscles, which will decrease your metabolism rate. However, if you add resistance training, and maintain or build muscles, you turn your body to a calories furnace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-better-posture&quot;&gt;6. Better posture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to our sedentary lifestyle, we might be facing muscular imbalances, such as weak back and tight hip flexors. Poor posture could possibly cause negative effects, such as back pain and lower confidence. With weight training, you could strengthen the weaker muscles and improve your posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-boost-self-esteem&quot;&gt;5. Boost self-esteem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you just begin to lift weights, you will notice that you are often setting personal record: lifting heavier weights, improving coordination and lifting more reps. This constant feedback of improvement will make you feel good about yourself and help to improve your self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-increase-focus&quot;&gt;4. Increase focus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you lift weights, you will have to focus on your breathing, posture and muscular contraction. Lifting weight with focus on the correct form will translate into increase in concentration on other aspects of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-become-happy&quot;&gt;3. Become happy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a happy pill, exercise is it! Yes, physical exercise lifts your mood and makes you happy. Weight lifting will work wonder for your mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-perform-better-in-other-sports&quot;&gt;2. Perform better in other sports&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting improves muscular strength, endurance and coordination. It also helps to prevent sports injuries. If you are already involve in other kind of sports, lifting weights will help you to perform better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-inspire-others&quot;&gt;1. Inspire others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People will notice your changes, be it your body, energy level, productivity or confidence level. They will ask you about your secret. This is your chance to make a difference to others by sharing the benefits of weight lifting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="weight lifting" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">Weight lifting saves my life. It is not merely about what happen in the gym. It is also about the transformation that occurs in my life. Besides looking better, I gain confidence, become more focus and achieve more in my life. Weight lifting has that power. Here are 11 ways that weight lifting changes your life. 11. You’ll look great Lifting weights help you to get lean and toned. You get the healthy shape you are looking for. Cardio might slim you down but you will never achieve that athletic look without implementing resistance training in your life. Ladies, do not worry about getting bulky, it takes a specific hypertrophy program and nutritional plan to gain mass. 10. Get stronger mentally As you get stronger physically, you will get stronger mentally. Often times, weight lifting requires you to persevere and push yourself to overcome the mental barriers and physical discomfort. It is about moving out of your comfort zone into your uncomfortable zone. If you repeat this simple act for enough time, you will expand your comfort zone. And that is how success happens. 9. Prevent osteoporosis Osteoporosis is a thinning of bone when the formation of new bone is slower than the depletion of bone. Therefore, the bones become brittle and are more prone to fracture. Weight lifting over a period of time can prevent bone loss and even increase bone density. 8. Improve balance Our core is the key to maintaining our balance. You need to activate your core during weight lifting, especially single leg exercises or asymmetrical exercises, to maintain your balance and posture. Through weight lifting, you get stronger in your core muscles and improve your balance. 7. Lose fats Weight lifting maintains/builds muscles, increases resting metabolic rate and improves insulin resistance, which are important factors in fat loss. When you only use cardio to manage your weight, you tend to lose fats and muscles, which will decrease your metabolism rate. However, if you add resistance training, and maintain or build muscles, you turn your body to a calories furnace. 6. Better posture Due to our sedentary lifestyle, we might be facing muscular imbalances, such as weak back and tight hip flexors. Poor posture could possibly cause negative effects, such as back pain and lower confidence. With weight training, you could strengthen the weaker muscles and improve your posture. 5. Boost self-esteem If you just begin to lift weights, you will notice that you are often setting personal record: lifting heavier weights, improving coordination and lifting more reps. This constant feedback of improvement will make you feel good about yourself and help to improve your self-esteem. 4. Increase focus When you lift weights, you will have to focus on your breathing, posture and muscular contraction. Lifting weight with focus on the correct form will translate into increase in concentration on other aspects of your life. 3. Become happy If there is a happy pill, exercise is it! Yes, physical exercise lifts your mood and makes you happy. Weight lifting will work wonder for your mental health. 2. Perform better in other sports Weight lifting improves muscular strength, endurance and coordination. It also helps to prevent sports injuries. If you are already involve in other kind of sports, lifting weights will help you to perform better. 1. Inspire others People will notice your changes, be it your body, energy level, productivity or confidence level. They will ask you about your secret. This is your chance to make a difference to others by sharing the benefits of weight lifting.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Combat your excuses: Try this 10 minutes body weight workout!</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/04/18/try-this-10-mins-workout/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Combat your excuses: Try this 10 minutes body weight workout!" /><published>2016-04-18T13:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-04-18T13:54:35+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/04/18/try-this-10-mins-workout</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/04/18/try-this-10-mins-workout/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;which-is-more-precious-time-or-health&quot;&gt;Which is more precious? Time or health?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, I hear people they do not have time to manage their health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is, in the long run, the lack of health maintenance will cost them more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do we have to choose between the two? Why do the both of them have to be mutually exclusive?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use to believe that if I miss one day of training, I will deteriorate. I use to practice yoga for 1 hour and dance for 1 hour. That’s not counting the time I have to travel to dance classes and watch dance videos. On top of that, I have to prepare my breakfast and lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If chronic obsession with dance is a thing, I have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder other aspects of my life are not going anywhere for me. Now, I exercise an hour a day, 3-5 days a week, and I feel much fitter, stronger and healthier. Some days, when things get hectic, I do 10 minutes body weight workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-am-in-better-balance&quot;&gt;I am in better balance.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am managing my time optimally. I know how to train smarter. I understand my priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I realize exercise comes after &lt;em&gt;non-exercise activity thermogenesis&lt;/em&gt; (NEAT) in the aspects of health.  NEAT is the calories expended outside of eating, exercising and sleeping. Basically becoming less sedentary, i.e. sitting less, should be looked into before contemplating about hitting the gym for an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be another me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t fall into the trap of thinking that more always equals to better.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steady state cardio workouts that last for more than 45 minutes have their own unique benefits. You can continue this form of exercise if you enjoy it. However, if you are someone like me, looking to slot in short bursts of workout in a time crammed lifestyle, here is a &lt;strong&gt;workout program that is just going to take you 10 minutes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-minutesbody-weight-workout&quot;&gt;10 minutes body weight workout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get your interval timer ready. The magic of short workout is in the burst of energy. It will only work if you push yourself to more than 70% of your effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–If you are new to circuit training, you want to work in 30s and rest for 30s. (Or feel free to go into any intervals that are more suitable for you.)
If you are familiar with circuit training, we are not going to take any rest. You are going to run through these 10 exercises in 1 minute interval each.–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;burpees&quot;&gt;Burpees&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From standing position, squat down and place both of your palms firmly on the floor. From this position either hop or walk back into a plank position. From the plank position, again, either hop or walk back into a squatting position. Explode into a jump or just stand and rise onto the balls of your feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;squats&quot;&gt;Squats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your feet are firmly grounded and aligned with your knee. Tighten your glutes muscles (butt). Hinge from your hips. Lead your squat with your glutes. Imagine that you are sitting down on a chair behind you. If you are fit, add an explosive hop when coming out from your squat position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-knees&quot;&gt;High knees&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have your hands in front of you at hips level. Lift your knees such that your knees touch your palms. Make sure you are not rounding your back in this exercise. Go as fast as you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rear-lunges&quot;&gt;Rear lunges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take your right foot back and go into a lunge position. Step back into lunge position. Alternate the feet that step back each time. If you feel that you could do more, switch legs with a hop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-plank-with-left-arm-on-floor&quot;&gt;Side plank with left arm on floor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engage your core and hold yourself up in a side plank position. If you feel strong, straighten your right arm, such that your arms and body form a t shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inchworm&quot;&gt;Inchworm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a standing position, bend forward such that your palms are down on the floor. Walk your hands out to a pushup position while keeping your legs straight. Walk your hands back towards your legs and straighten your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;side-plank-with-right-arm-on-floor&quot;&gt;Side plank with right arm on floor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is to balance out the previous side plank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;glute-bridge&quot;&gt;Glute bridge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lie supine with knees bend. Contract your glutes and lift into a bridge position, making sure not to compress your lower back. Lower yourself down without allowing your glutes to touch the floor. And lift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lateral-crawl&quot;&gt;Lateral crawl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start in a pushup position with your core tight. Cross your right arm over your left arm and move towards the left, coordinating the leg movements with the hands movement. Move 5 times to the left. And repeat on the right side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;elbow-plank&quot;&gt;Elbow plank&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have your elbows on the floor. Tighten all your muscles and go into a plank pose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you just finish a 10 minutes workout. If you still feel like going, repeat this round.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="body weight workout" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">Which is more precious? Time or health? Often, I hear people they do not have time to manage their health. The irony is, in the long run, the lack of health maintenance will cost them more time. Why do we have to choose between the two? Why do the both of them have to be mutually exclusive? I use to believe that if I miss one day of training, I will deteriorate. I use to practice yoga for 1 hour and dance for 1 hour. That’s not counting the time I have to travel to dance classes and watch dance videos. On top of that, I have to prepare my breakfast and lunch. If chronic obsession with dance is a thing, I have it. No wonder other aspects of my life are not going anywhere for me. Now, I exercise an hour a day, 3-5 days a week, and I feel much fitter, stronger and healthier. Some days, when things get hectic, I do 10 minutes body weight workout. I am in better balance. I am managing my time optimally. I know how to train smarter. I understand my priorities. In fact, I realize exercise comes after non-exercise activity thermogenesis (NEAT) in the aspects of health.  NEAT is the calories expended outside of eating, exercising and sleeping. Basically becoming less sedentary, i.e. sitting less, should be looked into before contemplating about hitting the gym for an hour. Don’t be another me. Don’t fall into the trap of thinking that more always equals to better. Steady state cardio workouts that last for more than 45 minutes have their own unique benefits. You can continue this form of exercise if you enjoy it. However, if you are someone like me, looking to slot in short bursts of workout in a time crammed lifestyle, here is a workout program that is just going to take you 10 minutes. 10 minutes body weight workout Get your interval timer ready. The magic of short workout is in the burst of energy. It will only work if you push yourself to more than 70% of your effort. –If you are new to circuit training, you want to work in 30s and rest for 30s. (Or feel free to go into any intervals that are more suitable for you.) If you are familiar with circuit training, we are not going to take any rest. You are going to run through these 10 exercises in 1 minute interval each.– Burpees From standing position, squat down and place both of your palms firmly on the floor. From this position either hop or walk back into a plank position. From the plank position, again, either hop or walk back into a squatting position. Explode into a jump or just stand and rise onto the balls of your feet. Squats Make sure your feet are firmly grounded and aligned with your knee. Tighten your glutes muscles (butt). Hinge from your hips. Lead your squat with your glutes. Imagine that you are sitting down on a chair behind you. If you are fit, add an explosive hop when coming out from your squat position. High knees Have your hands in front of you at hips level. Lift your knees such that your knees touch your palms. Make sure you are not rounding your back in this exercise. Go as fast as you can. Rear lunges Take your right foot back and go into a lunge position. Step back into lunge position. Alternate the feet that step back each time. If you feel that you could do more, switch legs with a hop. Side plank with left arm on floor Engage your core and hold yourself up in a side plank position. If you feel strong, straighten your right arm, such that your arms and body form a t shape. Inchworm From a standing position, bend forward such that your palms are down on the floor. Walk your hands out to a pushup position while keeping your legs straight. Walk your hands back towards your legs and straighten your body. Side plank with right arm on floor This is to balance out the previous side plank. Glute bridge Lie supine with knees bend. Contract your glutes and lift into a bridge position, making sure not to compress your lower back. Lower yourself down without allowing your glutes to touch the floor. And lift. Lateral crawl Start in a pushup position with your core tight. Cross your right arm over your left arm and move towards the left, coordinating the leg movements with the hands movement. Move 5 times to the left. And repeat on the right side. Elbow plank Have your elbows on the floor. Tighten all your muscles and go into a plank pose. And you just finish a 10 minutes workout. If you still feel like going, repeat this round.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How weight lifting saves my life</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/03/26/how-weight-lifting-saves-my-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How weight lifting saves my life" /><published>2016-03-26T13:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-03-26T13:54:35+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/03/26/how-weight-lifting-saves-my-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/03/26/how-weight-lifting-saves-my-life/">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt that you are not good enough for your role? I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a fitness instructor and I used to feel like I am a fraud. I am 1.63m with a weight of 54kg. I have a BMI of around 20 and that should be considered healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-the-truth-is-im-skinny-fat&quot;&gt;But the truth is I’m skinny fat.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am slim but I have muffin tops. Basically, I am flabby. And truth be told, when it comes to skinny for Asian, I am no where near that. I look into the mirror and I feel unconvincing. I did not suffer from body image issues but I believe I could be better. At the same time, my fitness career is going nowhere. Classes come and go. My financial and work life is a wreck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, the practice of yoga teaches me how to love and appreciate myself for who I am and for where I am at. I know I have to look forward and ignite the change necessary for me to become who I want to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-weight-lifting-comes-into-my-life&quot;&gt;And weight lifting comes into my life.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting knocks on my heart almost like how yoga comes into my life as an epiphany. I have faith in the calling of my heart. So far, it hasn’t failed me. It has always shown me the direction that I need to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, I got my friend to show me the ropes. Soon after, I find myself reading articles and books on weightlifting until I am confident enough to step into the gym alone. Today, I step in the gym with my own exercise plan. I lift the weights with a vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout my journey, I build up muscles and tone my body. And most importantly, I see the way I handle my business transform as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use to be passive, waiting for people to contact me for business. I used to share my services like I am not fully confident of it. Now, I’m actively networking and creating meaningful relationship. I am seeking out mentorship and surrounding myself with successful and wise people. I speak of my business with faith and conviction. Most importantly, I know my services are of high value and it could transform people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;because-i-have-been-through-the-transformation-myself&quot;&gt;Because I have been through the transformation myself.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the exhilaration that I feel when I lift 40kg off the floor. It’s the feeling that I got when I lift more than I did previously. It’s the focus that I need to lift in proper form. It’s the correction of my posture that gives me confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I stand in front of students, friends and strangers, knowing fully that I am good enough. Knowing that I understand different muscles groups and how they function. Knowing that I could guide a class safely and effectively. Knowing that my services work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weight-lifting-saves-my-life&quot;&gt;Weight lifting saves my life.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight lifting also reminds me that I could push pass my own mental limits and create records for myself. It shows me that progress comes with careful planning. At the same time, it shows me that I have to drop my ego in front of the weights, if not I will risk injuring myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In yoga, I am taught that our physical world is intricately linked to our internal world. How we do one thing is how we do everything. Through the internal workings, weight lifting brings upon to me a new world and possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-breaks-the-old-me-down&quot;&gt;It breaks the old me down.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new me is created and strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my life, I appreciate coming into contact with yoga and weightlifting. It challenges my perspective and allows me to learn more about life and myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today, I am at peace. Today, I am who I need to be.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="weight lifting" /><category term="self-esteem" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">Have you ever felt that you are not good enough for your role? I have. I am a fitness instructor and I used to feel like I am a fraud. I am 1.63m with a weight of 54kg. I have a BMI of around 20 and that should be considered healthy. But the truth is I’m skinny fat. I am slim but I have muffin tops. Basically, I am flabby. And truth be told, when it comes to skinny for Asian, I am no where near that. I look into the mirror and I feel unconvincing. I did not suffer from body image issues but I believe I could be better. At the same time, my fitness career is going nowhere. Classes come and go. My financial and work life is a wreck. Luckily, the practice of yoga teaches me how to love and appreciate myself for who I am and for where I am at. I know I have to look forward and ignite the change necessary for me to become who I want to be. And weight lifting comes into my life. Weight lifting knocks on my heart almost like how yoga comes into my life as an epiphany. I have faith in the calling of my heart. So far, it hasn’t failed me. It has always shown me the direction that I need to be. Initially, I got my friend to show me the ropes. Soon after, I find myself reading articles and books on weightlifting until I am confident enough to step into the gym alone. Today, I step in the gym with my own exercise plan. I lift the weights with a vision. Throughout my journey, I build up muscles and tone my body. And most importantly, I see the way I handle my business transform as well. I use to be passive, waiting for people to contact me for business. I used to share my services like I am not fully confident of it. Now, I’m actively networking and creating meaningful relationship. I am seeking out mentorship and surrounding myself with successful and wise people. I speak of my business with faith and conviction. Most importantly, I know my services are of high value and it could transform people. Because I have been through the transformation myself. It is the exhilaration that I feel when I lift 40kg off the floor. It’s the feeling that I got when I lift more than I did previously. It’s the focus that I need to lift in proper form. It’s the correction of my posture that gives me confidence. Today, I stand in front of students, friends and strangers, knowing fully that I am good enough. Knowing that I understand different muscles groups and how they function. Knowing that I could guide a class safely and effectively. Knowing that my services work. Weight lifting saves my life. Weight lifting also reminds me that I could push pass my own mental limits and create records for myself. It shows me that progress comes with careful planning. At the same time, it shows me that I have to drop my ego in front of the weights, if not I will risk injuring myself. In yoga, I am taught that our physical world is intricately linked to our internal world. How we do one thing is how we do everything. Through the internal workings, weight lifting brings upon to me a new world and possibilities. It breaks the old me down. A new me is created and strengthened. In my life, I appreciate coming into contact with yoga and weightlifting. It challenges my perspective and allows me to learn more about life and myself. Today, I am at peace. Today, I am who I need to be.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I’m a broke, ohm-chanting and time-altering dragon</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/musings/2016/02/21/im-a-broke-ohm-chanting-and-time-altering-dragon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I'm a broke, ohm-chanting and time-altering dragon" /><published>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/musings/2016/02/21/im-a-broke-ohm-chanting-and-time-altering-dragon</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/musings/2016/02/21/im-a-broke-ohm-chanting-and-time-altering-dragon/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;monday-tuesday-wednesday-to-saturday&quot;&gt;Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday to Saturday.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days repeat themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day, or maybe the same old yet different day. The escalator transports me upwards to the exit of the MRT station. It’s 3.25pm, work will start at 3.30pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am wearing a blue T-shirt that shouts volunteer at the back, and a knee-length navy blue yoga pants. I think I have worn them together last week and perhaps on a Tuesday too. Upon exiting the MRT station, a huge display screen of the shopping mall plays the same advertisement, which I can’t help but notice despite the fact that I never give much attention to this buzz. Most of the advertisements bully you to the way they think it is best for you to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-go-back-to-the-morning&quot;&gt;Let’s go back to the morning.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a yoga class, the weekly practice session that will prepare me to be a teacher. That is why I’m carrying my yoga mat to work. It starts at 10.30am, I must have reached around 10.35am. Everyone in class is sitting cross-legged with their eyes close, with the voice of my yoga teacher sailing through the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If there are divine beings, this is the place they will choose to reside.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to walk silently, not wanting my intrusion to break their focus. But the nature of the dance floor makes it impossible to take a step without announcing my arrival. It screeches away defiantly no matter how light I tread. Once, I remember I was lying down and somebody walked around my head and I thought I am going to be trample by an elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, with an outward look of poise, nobody so much as move even their eyes. If this is in a forest, a squirrel might just land on one of their laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not like them, I would be fidgeting and guessing who it is each time someone walks across the room. But luckily, they are not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I flow into the practice, feeling at ease and abandoning any thoughts that I have intruded the practice. Practice, in all solemnness should be practical and present. One should try to clear the disturbances of one’s mind during practice. It is to observe and let go whatever surfaces and bring our focus back to the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indeed, it is not going to be fairies prancing around magical toadstool or even prayer circles to wish for the ever elusive world peace, a slogan of the flower children in the hippie years, accompanied with long beards, filth-accumulating naked bodies and bare foot.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;at-12pm&quot;&gt;At 12pm.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We give our thanks and ready ourselves for the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of yoga is flow and the composure to face changes. The yoga class has ended and is ended. Today is the last day of our weekly session. It has been eight months since it all begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it feels that there is a deep transformational power within me, like a dragon arising from her century-long slumber, ready to soar. I’m ready for whatever the world is going to throw at me and I will face it with zen and peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are days which I thought I know what Buddha must have been through, living off nothing but feeling contentment and being dedicated to the arduous task of spreading his teachings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I live with nothing, relatively. I proclaim myself the great spiritual seeker who can subsist on the minimal. Of course, I can live with all this illusion until it is time to pay for my bills and I need to seek help from my parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-felt-like-a-hypocrite&quot;&gt;I felt like a hypocrite.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A balloon for chest puncture at this very moment. I cannot live next to nothing. For that, I’m sure Buddha doesn’t have to pay bills. Definitely the electricity, water and food did not come about because I sow seeds of love through the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything, of course is being well taken care of by my parents.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;18-march-2014&quot;&gt;18 March 2014.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might not be so different from 18 March 2010 after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I transform yet I am also back to where I begin, the lost and broke-ass kid of lofty dreams, living an idealistic life, traversing upon leaps and mountains of disapproval of others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, at twenty four, five years of searching, having been through what should be an incredible journey towards light and enlightenment, I am still in debts. The love did not manage to convince my local government to dissolve my debts. They would probably tell me to be grateful that they did not increase the interest rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-them-im-just-a-hobo&quot;&gt;To them, I’m just a hobo.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so be it. God, Buddha, or whoever up there did not patronize my efforts of tender love towards their creations or universal consciousness or oneness or divinity or nothingness. I am not even close, maybe I’m the wolf in sheep clothing in the spiritual world, in which I believe that I’m a sheep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;year-2014&quot;&gt;Year 2014.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still greedy and with many desires in my life that it is in complete opposition in the practice of contentment. Even when it is nearing the end of my yoga teacher training, I am still sitting on the fence of six thousand dollars of debt (my polytechnic school fees and part of my yoga teacher training fees) and of living off my parents shamelessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when I’m positioned precariously, with the danger of falling to the abyss of immobility, I am planning for my next dive trip, hankering for Bali to learn tribal fusion belly dance and even dreaming of scoring a permaculture certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still after eight months of yoga pursuit, in which I learn that yoga essentially means a state of clarity, I am an unstable and highly unreliable human being.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of becoming more clear-eyed about the one thing that I should devote myself to, I morph into a multi-headed, ohm-chanting, serene looking, juice-sipping dragon or if you prefer wolf in sheep’s skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I discredit myself any further, there is at least one thing that I am living in accordance to the philosophy of yoga. It is that I should do my best without attaching myself to the results. I’m taking this path seriously and flowing with the wind throughout my efforts to soar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am biologically twenty four, spiritually nutcase, monetary broke, but at least physically and mentally, I feel at my best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if my erected spine has free itself from the messy affair with gravity. The lower half of my body is grounded like it should be, but I could stand as if heaven has attached a string to my upper half of my body. Maybe there is a help line send from up above after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am without traces of age lines on my face, without the impairment of the spine through constant slouching in modern day living. With my suppleness, I am going through the best ride of my life, at this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe, I turn back time or maybe the way I’m living is simply topsy-turvy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems yesterday is a far shot but eight months ago is just within stretch and tomorrow, who knows. Time is a funny thing and the only logical thing one could do is to be present. And maybe, if I hang on a little more, I would have wings strong enough to soar with the multi heads of my greedy dragon. I would be able to piece it all together and live through it as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But now is not the time to worry because I am truly at the best moment of my life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><category term="live your dream" /><category term="passion" /><summary type="html">Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday to Saturday. These days repeat themselves. Another day, or maybe the same old yet different day. The escalator transports me upwards to the exit of the MRT station. It’s 3.25pm, work will start at 3.30pm. I am wearing a blue T-shirt that shouts volunteer at the back, and a knee-length navy blue yoga pants. I think I have worn them together last week and perhaps on a Tuesday too. Upon exiting the MRT station, a huge display screen of the shopping mall plays the same advertisement, which I can’t help but notice despite the fact that I never give much attention to this buzz. Most of the advertisements bully you to the way they think it is best for you to live. Let’s go back to the morning. I have a yoga class, the weekly practice session that will prepare me to be a teacher. That is why I’m carrying my yoga mat to work. It starts at 10.30am, I must have reached around 10.35am. Everyone in class is sitting cross-legged with their eyes close, with the voice of my yoga teacher sailing through the air. If there are divine beings, this is the place they will choose to reside. I try to walk silently, not wanting my intrusion to break their focus. But the nature of the dance floor makes it impossible to take a step without announcing my arrival. It screeches away defiantly no matter how light I tread. Once, I remember I was lying down and somebody walked around my head and I thought I am going to be trample by an elephant. Still, with an outward look of poise, nobody so much as move even their eyes. If this is in a forest, a squirrel might just land on one of their laps. I am not like them, I would be fidgeting and guessing who it is each time someone walks across the room. But luckily, they are not me. I flow into the practice, feeling at ease and abandoning any thoughts that I have intruded the practice. Practice, in all solemnness should be practical and present. One should try to clear the disturbances of one’s mind during practice. It is to observe and let go whatever surfaces and bring our focus back to the practice. Indeed, it is not going to be fairies prancing around magical toadstool or even prayer circles to wish for the ever elusive world peace, a slogan of the flower children in the hippie years, accompanied with long beards, filth-accumulating naked bodies and bare foot. At 12pm. We give our thanks and ready ourselves for the world. The beauty of yoga is flow and the composure to face changes. The yoga class has ended and is ended. Today is the last day of our weekly session. It has been eight months since it all begins. Sometimes it feels that there is a deep transformational power within me, like a dragon arising from her century-long slumber, ready to soar. I’m ready for whatever the world is going to throw at me and I will face it with zen and peace. Yes, there are days which I thought I know what Buddha must have been through, living off nothing but feeling contentment and being dedicated to the arduous task of spreading his teachings. Because I live with nothing, relatively. I proclaim myself the great spiritual seeker who can subsist on the minimal. Of course, I can live with all this illusion until it is time to pay for my bills and I need to seek help from my parents. I felt like a hypocrite. A balloon for chest puncture at this very moment. I cannot live next to nothing. For that, I’m sure Buddha doesn’t have to pay bills. Definitely the electricity, water and food did not come about because I sow seeds of love through the universe. Everything, of course is being well taken care of by my parents. 18 March 2014. It might not be so different from 18 March 2010 after all. I transform yet I am also back to where I begin, the lost and broke-ass kid of lofty dreams, living an idealistic life, traversing upon leaps and mountains of disapproval of others. Today, at twenty four, five years of searching, having been through what should be an incredible journey towards light and enlightenment, I am still in debts. The love did not manage to convince my local government to dissolve my debts. They would probably tell me to be grateful that they did not increase the interest rate. To them, I’m just a hobo. And so be it. God, Buddha, or whoever up there did not patronize my efforts of tender love towards their creations or universal consciousness or oneness or divinity or nothingness. I am not even close, maybe I’m the wolf in sheep clothing in the spiritual world, in which I believe that I’m a sheep. Year 2014. I am still greedy and with many desires in my life that it is in complete opposition in the practice of contentment. Even when it is nearing the end of my yoga teacher training, I am still sitting on the fence of six thousand dollars of debt (my polytechnic school fees and part of my yoga teacher training fees) and of living off my parents shamelessly. Even when I’m positioned precariously, with the danger of falling to the abyss of immobility, I am planning for my next dive trip, hankering for Bali to learn tribal fusion belly dance and even dreaming of scoring a permaculture certification. Still after eight months of yoga pursuit, in which I learn that yoga essentially means a state of clarity, I am an unstable and highly unreliable human being. Instead of becoming more clear-eyed about the one thing that I should devote myself to, I morph into a multi-headed, ohm-chanting, serene looking, juice-sipping dragon or if you prefer wolf in sheep’s skin. Before I discredit myself any further, there is at least one thing that I am living in accordance to the philosophy of yoga. It is that I should do my best without attaching myself to the results. I’m taking this path seriously and flowing with the wind throughout my efforts to soar. Today. I am biologically twenty four, spiritually nutcase, monetary broke, but at least physically and mentally, I feel at my best. As if my erected spine has free itself from the messy affair with gravity. The lower half of my body is grounded like it should be, but I could stand as if heaven has attached a string to my upper half of my body. Maybe there is a help line send from up above after all. I am without traces of age lines on my face, without the impairment of the spine through constant slouching in modern day living. With my suppleness, I am going through the best ride of my life, at this moment. Maybe, I turn back time or maybe the way I’m living is simply topsy-turvy. It seems yesterday is a far shot but eight months ago is just within stretch and tomorrow, who knows. Time is a funny thing and the only logical thing one could do is to be present. And maybe, if I hang on a little more, I would have wings strong enough to soar with the multi heads of my greedy dragon. I would be able to piece it all together and live through it as a whole. But now is not the time to worry because I am truly at the best moment of my life.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lets be an artist now</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/musings/2016/02/21/lets-be-an-artist-now/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lets be an artist now" /><published>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/musings/2016/02/21/lets-be-an-artist-now</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/musings/2016/02/21/lets-be-an-artist-now/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;for-this-moment-sit-alone&quot;&gt;For this moment, sit alone.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allow the buzz of the world to pass and listen closely to your heart’s desire. Perhaps, you would hear this voice inside of you. This voice is urging you shyly, slowly but surely, like a tortoise emerging from its’ shell. It could be so soft that it is almost inaudible to you, because you have never given it too much attention. But give it a little more time, you would hear that this voice in you is crying out for you to play, to play boundlessly and freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It wishes for you to celebrate the moment and simply live in the now.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are patient to realize, you hear that this voice is nurturing an artist. Not the hot shot mega million rock star kind of artist, but the artist who is approachable, the artist, who is someone real, someone like you. There is an artist in you waiting to emerge if only you believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;we-are-all-born-to-create&quot;&gt;We are all born to create.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spend much of our childhood imagining that we are captains sailing the ferocious sea, the jungle explorers stumbling on the next miracle herb for mankind, or even the sages working to solve the puzzle of the grand web of life. Of course, we might have one or two teddy bears which we would do voice over for. And we host our own kids’ entertainment channel, on par with Teletubbies and Blue Clues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The world is full of possibilities and magic.&lt;/strong&gt;
Then, we go to school where creating become mandatory, more than that, creativity becomes a chore and is stuffed into a box of grades and criticism. At the same time, we have to manage living in the cauldron of grades, expectations, mini-skirts, and the funny feeling towards the opposite sex. Bit by bit, we lose that little connection with simply making things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, I say it, creating art isn’t anything noble, it isn’t all about creating The Last Supper, Mona Lisa or David. Yes, it could become something recognized, but art, strips to its’ base, is just making things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;art-is-play&quot;&gt;Art is play.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The word play is defiant, it rejects fitting into a singular form.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Play could involve legos, words, bodily movements, colors, flowers, cars, papers, photos, aubergines, chickpeas, knives, seedlings and so much more. Play would involve destruction and creation, no matter which form it takes. Even writers have to continuously depart with words they love. Art is a micro version of nature, the constant cycle of destruction and creation. Perhaps it is this reason why one could feel so much alive and at one with the universe when creating art. Some would call this experience being in the flow. Whatever you call it, it is real and so real that sometimes everything else becomes an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you create art, you chuck the ominous question of the purpose of one’s existence to one side.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could leave that to the philosophers to figure and argue among them for now. At this moment, when you are at one with your art, your soul resonates with the rhythm of the universe. And it is particularly in this state that you understand that this is all that you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;all-the-layers-of-crises-fall-apart-and&quot;&gt;All the layers of crises fall apart. and&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others might ask if this is your form of escapade from the reality. And perhaps, this is the time to retrieve the question on the purpose of one existence and to question reality. What is reality exactly? Is it this environment of sterility and control whereby your every action could be spied by a particular person? Is it reality where you have to be living under surveillance and thronging among the crowd anonymously? Is this what is to be perceived as reality? The subject of reality is as broad as play could be, so why would one shackle another on the threat of reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##So please don’t let the voices of others drown the timid voice in you.##&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could be a dancer feeling the vibrations of music in our limbs, or a poet riding the tempo of words, or a photographer capturing the light of fleeting nature into eternity. This you could all be and even more in your life. You could be a low-wage worker, a farmer, a white collar, a top-level executive or a medical doctor. Whatever it is, you need not be in constant conflict with the voice crying out to create art. Because art transcends the boundaries of identities and labels. And through art, you would discover that you have lost yourself only to ultimately reconnect with the universe once more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Only if you listen to that timid voice inside you.
Only if you take the courage to step in faith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, through many cycles of construction, destruction, agony, happiness, emptiness, contentment, separation, unity and transcending, your world could never be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="finding motivation" /><category term="passion" /><category term="live your dream" /><summary type="html">For this moment, sit alone. Allow the buzz of the world to pass and listen closely to your heart’s desire. Perhaps, you would hear this voice inside of you. This voice is urging you shyly, slowly but surely, like a tortoise emerging from its’ shell. It could be so soft that it is almost inaudible to you, because you have never given it too much attention. But give it a little more time, you would hear that this voice in you is crying out for you to play, to play boundlessly and freely. It wishes for you to celebrate the moment and simply live in the now. If you are patient to realize, you hear that this voice is nurturing an artist. Not the hot shot mega million rock star kind of artist, but the artist who is approachable, the artist, who is someone real, someone like you. There is an artist in you waiting to emerge if only you believe. We are all born to create. We spend much of our childhood imagining that we are captains sailing the ferocious sea, the jungle explorers stumbling on the next miracle herb for mankind, or even the sages working to solve the puzzle of the grand web of life. Of course, we might have one or two teddy bears which we would do voice over for. And we host our own kids’ entertainment channel, on par with Teletubbies and Blue Clues. The world is full of possibilities and magic. Then, we go to school where creating become mandatory, more than that, creativity becomes a chore and is stuffed into a box of grades and criticism. At the same time, we have to manage living in the cauldron of grades, expectations, mini-skirts, and the funny feeling towards the opposite sex. Bit by bit, we lose that little connection with simply making things up. There, I say it, creating art isn’t anything noble, it isn’t all about creating The Last Supper, Mona Lisa or David. Yes, it could become something recognized, but art, strips to its’ base, is just making things up. Art is play. The word play is defiant, it rejects fitting into a singular form. Play could involve legos, words, bodily movements, colors, flowers, cars, papers, photos, aubergines, chickpeas, knives, seedlings and so much more. Play would involve destruction and creation, no matter which form it takes. Even writers have to continuously depart with words they love. Art is a micro version of nature, the constant cycle of destruction and creation. Perhaps it is this reason why one could feel so much alive and at one with the universe when creating art. Some would call this experience being in the flow. Whatever you call it, it is real and so real that sometimes everything else becomes an illusion. When you create art, you chuck the ominous question of the purpose of one’s existence to one side. You could leave that to the philosophers to figure and argue among them for now. At this moment, when you are at one with your art, your soul resonates with the rhythm of the universe. And it is particularly in this state that you understand that this is all that you need. All the layers of crises fall apart. and They cease to exist. Others might ask if this is your form of escapade from the reality. And perhaps, this is the time to retrieve the question on the purpose of one existence and to question reality. What is reality exactly? Is it this environment of sterility and control whereby your every action could be spied by a particular person? Is it reality where you have to be living under surveillance and thronging among the crowd anonymously? Is this what is to be perceived as reality? The subject of reality is as broad as play could be, so why would one shackle another on the threat of reality? ##So please don’t let the voices of others drown the timid voice in you.## You could be a dancer feeling the vibrations of music in our limbs, or a poet riding the tempo of words, or a photographer capturing the light of fleeting nature into eternity. This you could all be and even more in your life. You could be a low-wage worker, a farmer, a white collar, a top-level executive or a medical doctor. Whatever it is, you need not be in constant conflict with the voice crying out to create art. Because art transcends the boundaries of identities and labels. And through art, you would discover that you have lost yourself only to ultimately reconnect with the universe once more. ##Only if you listen to that timid voice inside you. Only if you take the courage to step in faith. Then, through many cycles of construction, destruction, agony, happiness, emptiness, contentment, separation, unity and transcending, your world could never be the same again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 ways to increase your commitment to weight management program</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/02/21/4-ways-to-increase-commitment-to-weight-loss/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 ways to increase your commitment to weight management program" /><published>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</published><updated>2016-02-21T18:54:35+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/02/21/4-ways-to-increase-commitment-to-weight-loss</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/fitness/2016/02/21/4-ways-to-increase-commitment-to-weight-loss/">&lt;p&gt;What is the first thing that you think about when people mention weight loss?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people will conjure up images of deprivation. Not being able to eat the food they like. Endless exercises. Running like a gazelle. Giving up the comfort of their cosy chair. Moving around a place full of self-obsessed people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is precisely this line of thought that prevents people from starting a weight management program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I did not start out loving the gym.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were to tell me 5 years ago that I will love hanging out in the gym, I will think that you are crazy. I’m not selling you a castle in the cloud, I’m talking about sustainable changes that will stage you up for success in your weight management program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I’m going to tell you how you could increase your commitment to weight management plan and avoid the pitfall of self-sabotaging behaviors like “I’m not good enough”, “It’s too scary” or “I’m never getting there”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-start-easy&quot;&gt;4. Start easy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you apply for CEO when you just graduate from school? Changes are you start as an executive on the lower management level. So why is it that when people approach weight loss, they change their diet and exercise from one extreme to the other extreme? After a few days, they start to have cravings and they have to struggle with their willpower. Yes, some people have super willpower to succeed this way. But for one person that succeed, there are many more who will scrap their diet change as a failure and think that there is no point in doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s much easier to start with small changes and work towards your ultimate goal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are just starting out, even eating one healthy meal or exercising once a week is a great start. Once it becomes habitual, you can start increasing the amount of healthy food, cutting the calories and exercising more regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-have-a-structured-plan&quot;&gt;3. Have a structured plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not always a fan of having a structured plan. But over the years, I feel that having a structured plan will reduce my needs to rely on my emotions to make decision. Of course, it is great that if you are feeling motivated and are hitting the gym, exercising regularly and eating clean. But what happen if you are not feeling your very best and decide to skip the gym for one day, and then the next, and then the next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Having a structured plan reduces the guesswork and need to rely on willpower.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it as specify as possible. If Thursday is your legs day, on Wednesday night, plan out the time you are going to the gym, exact exercises, reps, sets. I will go so far as to even plan the rest time in between sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-let-go-of-perfectionism&quot;&gt;2. Let go of perfectionism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is normal for hiccups to happen.&lt;strong&gt;A structured plan is important but flexibility is also key.&lt;/strong&gt; If this sounds paradoxical, let me explain further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be unforeseen circumstances. Let’s say your family got into an accident, you won’t be sticking to your gym plan. And there is also something called the holidays. Rather than giving up on your exercise plan because you have been missing out on four days or even weeks, continue from where you stop and keep on going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are embarking on a weight management program, you ought to be giving yourself a huge applaud for taking a conscious step to make changes. The last thing you want to do is to beat yourself out with notions that you are undisciplined and destined to fail. Let go of all of this and take every new opportunity to work towards your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-identify-the-importance-of-weight-loss-in-your-life&quot;&gt;1. Identify the importance of weight loss in your life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the effective ways to encourage people to stay on a weight management program is for them to identify the importance of the weight loss in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have been living an unhealthy lifestyle for 20-40 years, you need to find motivation: reasons for you to exercise and eat clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation comes in different forms: extrinsic, intrinsic and a combination of extrinsic and intrinsic.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extrinsic motivation are external factors that motivate you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be advice from doctors and suggestion from the spouse. This form of motivation may encourage you initially but they seldom provide long term motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to also explore the intrinsic motivation of your weight loss, which is your own personal achievement that you can derive from the behavioral change. It can be things like less stress. Lastly, these motivations do not have to be mutually exclusive. You can combine them to motivate yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="weight management program" /><category term="gym" /><category term="weight loss" /><summary type="html">What is the first thing that you think about when people mention weight loss? Many people will conjure up images of deprivation. Not being able to eat the food they like. Endless exercises. Running like a gazelle. Giving up the comfort of their cosy chair. Moving around a place full of self-obsessed people. It is precisely this line of thought that prevents people from starting a weight management program. I did not start out loving the gym. If you were to tell me 5 years ago that I will love hanging out in the gym, I will think that you are crazy. I’m not selling you a castle in the cloud, I’m talking about sustainable changes that will stage you up for success in your weight management program. Today, I’m going to tell you how you could increase your commitment to weight management plan and avoid the pitfall of self-sabotaging behaviors like “I’m not good enough”, “It’s too scary” or “I’m never getting there”. 4. Start easy Do you apply for CEO when you just graduate from school? Changes are you start as an executive on the lower management level. So why is it that when people approach weight loss, they change their diet and exercise from one extreme to the other extreme? After a few days, they start to have cravings and they have to struggle with their willpower. Yes, some people have super willpower to succeed this way. But for one person that succeed, there are many more who will scrap their diet change as a failure and think that there is no point in doing it. It’s much easier to start with small changes and work towards your ultimate goal. If you are just starting out, even eating one healthy meal or exercising once a week is a great start. Once it becomes habitual, you can start increasing the amount of healthy food, cutting the calories and exercising more regularly. 3. Have a structured plan I’m not always a fan of having a structured plan. But over the years, I feel that having a structured plan will reduce my needs to rely on my emotions to make decision. Of course, it is great that if you are feeling motivated and are hitting the gym, exercising regularly and eating clean. But what happen if you are not feeling your very best and decide to skip the gym for one day, and then the next, and then the next? Having a structured plan reduces the guesswork and need to rely on willpower. Make it as specify as possible. If Thursday is your legs day, on Wednesday night, plan out the time you are going to the gym, exact exercises, reps, sets. I will go so far as to even plan the rest time in between sets. 2. Let go of perfectionism It is normal for hiccups to happen.A structured plan is important but flexibility is also key. If this sounds paradoxical, let me explain further. There will be unforeseen circumstances. Let’s say your family got into an accident, you won’t be sticking to your gym plan. And there is also something called the holidays. Rather than giving up on your exercise plan because you have been missing out on four days or even weeks, continue from where you stop and keep on going. When you are embarking on a weight management program, you ought to be giving yourself a huge applaud for taking a conscious step to make changes. The last thing you want to do is to beat yourself out with notions that you are undisciplined and destined to fail. Let go of all of this and take every new opportunity to work towards your goal. 1. Identify the importance of weight loss in your life One of the effective ways to encourage people to stay on a weight management program is for them to identify the importance of the weight loss in their lives. If you have been living an unhealthy lifestyle for 20-40 years, you need to find motivation: reasons for you to exercise and eat clean. Motivation comes in different forms: extrinsic, intrinsic and a combination of extrinsic and intrinsic. Extrinsic motivation are external factors that motivate you. It can be advice from doctors and suggestion from the spouse. This form of motivation may encourage you initially but they seldom provide long term motivation. You want to also explore the intrinsic motivation of your weight loss, which is your own personal achievement that you can derive from the behavioral change. It can be things like less stress. Lastly, these motivations do not have to be mutually exclusive. You can combine them to motivate yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Motivational Read for 25-Year-Old</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/musings/2015/12/05/a-motivational-read-for-25-year-old/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Motivational Read for 25-Year-Old" /><published>2015-12-05T18:56:21+08:00</published><updated>2015-12-05T18:56:21+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/musings/2015/12/05/a-motivational-read-for-25-year-old</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/musings/2015/12/05/a-motivational-read-for-25-year-old/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;life&quot;&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encounters of cheats and scam artists. Failures, disappointments and scorn. Because of those, you might have grown a little skeptical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your world of dreams might have shrunk a little.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know there is no pot of gold at the end of the rainbow. It hurts more when you learn that the end of the rainbow is nothing but an optical illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intersection&quot;&gt;Intersection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adventures, love and dreams. And hopefully more tales to come. You are at the peak of your young adulthood. 4 years ago, you officially become an adult, you become legal in the eyes of justice. 5 more years, you are going into your big 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe the world isn’t so hostile after all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You manage to meet helpful strangers, who become friends. If you are fortunate enough, you might too have found your soul mate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you still remember how it is like for you 10 years back? When you are still a teen? When you look to the adults and think to yourself how they seem to have it all. No homework, no exams, no deadlines. Glitz and glam. Holidays and cruise. Photos to show it all off. And money to spend on things that they like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions&quot;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is it like for you now? Back to your reality. Now, you are at where they are, 25. Maybe you still do not have your life together. But you get a glimpse to the social issues: economic crisis, inequality, prejudices and political unrest. You remember saying that you are going to change the world and make the world a better place. You are younger then and you hold wild ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps now, at the age of 25, you still do not have any clear directions on how to achieve that. But you know better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You know that not knowing could be more of the norm.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 25, you meet mentors and people of different age group and you realise it is common for people to not have a clue on what is going on with their lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s okay, you’re only 25. Your commitments are rising but hopefully you’re out of debt. Maybe you’ve been bumming around for the past 25 years. However, you can still make the choice to pick things up over the next 25 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to make the decision now. You don’t have time to waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now&quot;&gt;Now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You only have this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have yet to do so, now is the time to live so hard that you don’t look back in regrets. Wake up everyday and choose to hustle. You might not know exactly what your purpose in life is yet. But just keep working on it, grab opportunities as they come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You never know when you will chance upon your calling, so don’t avoid the toil.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your purpose won’t fall from the sky if all you do is to talk about it. Go far and go broad in search of it. When you find it, stay on it with laser-like focus. Sometimes it is not about following your heart, it is about recognizing the potential in the path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are possibilities and opportunities to explore. You might end up on the wrong side of the path but allow these experiences to make you stronger and kinder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do good, create, try new things, be open to love, reflect at the end of the day and talk to strangers. Experiment with a new recipe, watch a documentary, fall asleep under the stars and volunteer for a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are 25. Some people never live to that age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is great just to be alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;today&quot;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great time to create your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, do that every single day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><category term="live your dream" /><summary type="html">Life Encounters of cheats and scam artists. Failures, disappointments and scorn. Because of those, you might have grown a little skeptical. Your world of dreams might have shrunk a little. You know there is no pot of gold at the end of the rainbow. It hurts more when you learn that the end of the rainbow is nothing but an optical illusion. Intersection Adventures, love and dreams. And hopefully more tales to come. You are at the peak of your young adulthood. 4 years ago, you officially become an adult, you become legal in the eyes of justice. 5 more years, you are going into your big 3. Maybe the world isn’t so hostile after all. You manage to meet helpful strangers, who become friends. If you are fortunate enough, you might too have found your soul mate. Do you still remember how it is like for you 10 years back? When you are still a teen? When you look to the adults and think to yourself how they seem to have it all. No homework, no exams, no deadlines. Glitz and glam. Holidays and cruise. Photos to show it all off. And money to spend on things that they like. Questions How is it like for you now? Back to your reality. Now, you are at where they are, 25. Maybe you still do not have your life together. But you get a glimpse to the social issues: economic crisis, inequality, prejudices and political unrest. You remember saying that you are going to change the world and make the world a better place. You are younger then and you hold wild ambitions. Perhaps now, at the age of 25, you still do not have any clear directions on how to achieve that. But you know better. You know that not knowing could be more of the norm. By 25, you meet mentors and people of different age group and you realise it is common for people to not have a clue on what is going on with their lives. But it’s okay, you’re only 25. Your commitments are rising but hopefully you’re out of debt. Maybe you’ve been bumming around for the past 25 years. However, you can still make the choice to pick things up over the next 25 years. You need to make the decision now. You don’t have time to waste. Now You only have this moment. If you have yet to do so, now is the time to live so hard that you don’t look back in regrets. Wake up everyday and choose to hustle. You might not know exactly what your purpose in life is yet. But just keep working on it, grab opportunities as they come. You never know when you will chance upon your calling, so don’t avoid the toil. Your purpose won’t fall from the sky if all you do is to talk about it. Go far and go broad in search of it. When you find it, stay on it with laser-like focus. Sometimes it is not about following your heart, it is about recognizing the potential in the path. There are possibilities and opportunities to explore. You might end up on the wrong side of the path but allow these experiences to make you stronger and kinder. Do good, create, try new things, be open to love, reflect at the end of the day and talk to strangers. Experiment with a new recipe, watch a documentary, fall asleep under the stars and volunteer for a cause. You are 25. Some people never live to that age. It is great just to be alive. Today A great time to create your life. Now, do that every single day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An important life lesson from 1 burn, 2 fractured bones and 3 lacerations</title><link href="thegeekwing.com/musings/2015/11/29/one-life-lesson-from-my-injuries/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An important life lesson from 1 burn, 2 fractured bones and 3 lacerations" /><published>2015-11-29T19:56:21+08:00</published><updated>2015-11-29T19:56:21+08:00</updated><id>thegeekwing.com/musings/2015/11/29/one-life-lesson-from-my-injuries</id><content type="html" xml:base="thegeekwing.com/musings/2015/11/29/one-life-lesson-from-my-injuries/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;24-novmeber-2015-i-crash&quot;&gt;24 Novmeber 2015. I crash.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And need stitches on 3 parts of my body: the left elbow, side of my left thigh and my left knee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am in Bali, with plans to climb Mt Agung, Bali’s highest mountain, an elevation of 3031m, on that evening. Now, it won’t be happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9.47am, I have 3 gaping wounds, some scratches and a limp. It is my 3rd day of travel, I have a total of 7 days in Bali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3rd-day-of-travel&quot;&gt;3rd day of travel.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am lying on the bed of the 3rd hospital they send me to. Local anesthesia is injected around my wounds. At 12.08pm, I am in stitches and bandages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have felt bad for myself. But I smile and tell everyone else that all is fine and gracefully accept any help that come my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next 4 days, I treat myself to lots of organic food and ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6th-day-in-bali&quot;&gt;6th day in Bali.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am given an opportunity to teach a short English class in a local village school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not rush off from plans to plans, places to places. It is a slow holiday. Every morning, I relax at my hostel, Rama Sita, which overlooks beautiful stretches of rice field. When there is someone in the hostel, I enjoy their company. When there is no one around, I rejoice in the silence and peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not the first time that something major happen to my body. At 19, I have 2 incidents of fractured right collar bones. At 23, I have a 2-inch burn on my left leg from the motor exhaust pipe during my travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have been upset over my negligence. I could have chosen to focus on the pain that I have brought upon myself over and over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-i-choose-to-be-grateful&quot;&gt;But I choose to be grateful.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grateful that things did not turn out worse. Grateful that I can choose to smile. I will not allow myself to be miserable despite my circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, things turn out well. Because of my fracture, I am able to attend an exchange program in school. Otherwise, I will have to remain in my internship, which I’m not enjoying. Because of my burnt mark, I have a great ice breaker story. Because of my recent accident, I am treated with kindness and unexpected surprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scars will probably remain for a long time on my body as a reminder to be more cautious. But I won’t let them constrict me. They will not stop me from being in the moment that I am in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am to feel grieve, I will stay in that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I am to feel joy, I will too stay in that moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever may come, I see them as valuable experiences and life lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unexpected events happen. Changes are common. Often time, we might feel safer living in the constant and frazzled over changes. But it is up to us to be affected negatively or positively by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-resilience&quot;&gt;This is resilience.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is the life lesson I receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learn to allow myself to blossom to rise above my current adversity. I learn that It is about managing my behaviors, thoughts and actions. It is about processing my emotional distress. It is about managing them so that they don’t stop me from normal functioning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are all human, we will feel strong emotions should adversity or trauma arises. Being resilient won’t make the problems go away. But being resilient will enhance our abilities to handle them more effectively. We can choose to bounce back or to fall apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my life, I choose to bounce back, no matter how hard I fall. Sometimes, I will stay a long time in my fall, but I will definitely rise again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-moment&quot;&gt;This moment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only time I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will choose to make the best out of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><category term="live your dream" /><summary type="html">24 Novmeber 2015. I crash. And need stitches on 3 parts of my body: the left elbow, side of my left thigh and my left knee. I am in Bali, with plans to climb Mt Agung, Bali’s highest mountain, an elevation of 3031m, on that evening. Now, it won’t be happening. 9.47am, I have 3 gaping wounds, some scratches and a limp. It is my 3rd day of travel, I have a total of 7 days in Bali. 3rd day of travel. I am lying on the bed of the 3rd hospital they send me to. Local anesthesia is injected around my wounds. At 12.08pm, I am in stitches and bandages. I could have felt bad for myself. But I smile and tell everyone else that all is fine and gracefully accept any help that come my way. The next 4 days, I treat myself to lots of organic food and ice cream. 6th day in Bali. I am given an opportunity to teach a short English class in a local village school. I did not rush off from plans to plans, places to places. It is a slow holiday. Every morning, I relax at my hostel, Rama Sita, which overlooks beautiful stretches of rice field. When there is someone in the hostel, I enjoy their company. When there is no one around, I rejoice in the silence and peace. It is not the first time that something major happen to my body. At 19, I have 2 incidents of fractured right collar bones. At 23, I have a 2-inch burn on my left leg from the motor exhaust pipe during my travel. I could have been upset over my negligence. I could have chosen to focus on the pain that I have brought upon myself over and over. But I choose to be grateful. Grateful that things did not turn out worse. Grateful that I can choose to smile. I will not allow myself to be miserable despite my circumstances. In the end, things turn out well. Because of my fracture, I am able to attend an exchange program in school. Otherwise, I will have to remain in my internship, which I’m not enjoying. Because of my burnt mark, I have a great ice breaker story. Because of my recent accident, I am treated with kindness and unexpected surprises. The scars will probably remain for a long time on my body as a reminder to be more cautious. But I won’t let them constrict me. They will not stop me from being in the moment that I am in. If I am to feel grieve, I will stay in that moment. If I am to feel joy, I will too stay in that moment. Whatever may come, I see them as valuable experiences and life lessons. Unexpected events happen. Changes are common. Often time, we might feel safer living in the constant and frazzled over changes. But it is up to us to be affected negatively or positively by them. This is resilience. And this is the life lesson I receive. I learn to allow myself to blossom to rise above my current adversity. I learn that It is about managing my behaviors, thoughts and actions. It is about processing my emotional distress. It is about managing them so that they don’t stop me from normal functioning. We are all human, we will feel strong emotions should adversity or trauma arises. Being resilient won’t make the problems go away. But being resilient will enhance our abilities to handle them more effectively. We can choose to bounce back or to fall apart. In my life, I choose to bounce back, no matter how hard I fall. Sometimes, I will stay a long time in my fall, but I will definitely rise again. This moment The only time I have. And I will choose to make the best out of it.</summary></entry></feed>